<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
"http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  NOTE:  This XML file is input used to produce the authoritative copy of an
  OpenID Foundation specification.  The authoritative copy is the HTML output.
  This XML source file is not authoritative.  The statement ipr="none" is
  present only to satisfy the document compilation tool and is not indicative
  of the IPR status of this specification.  The IPR for this specification is
  described in the "Notices" section.  This is a public OpenID Foundation
  document and not a private document, as the private="..." declaration could
  be taken to indicate.
-->
<rfc category="std" docName="openid-connect-federation-05" ipr="none">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="OpenID Connect Federation">OpenID Connect Federation 1.0 -
    draft 05</title>

    <author fullname="Roland Hedberg" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Hedberg">
      <organization>independent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>roland@catalogix.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andreas &Aring;kre Solberg" initials="A.&Aring;."
            surname="Solberg">
      <organization abbrev="Uninett">Uninett AS</organization>

      <address>
        <email>andreas.solberg@uninett.no</email>

        <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreassolberg/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Samuel Gulliksson" initials="S." surname="Gulliksson">
      <organization abbrev="Schibsted">Schibsted Media Group</organization>

      <address>
        <email>samuel.gulliksson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>

      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>

        <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.thread-safe.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="17" month="September" year="2018"/>

    <workgroup>OpenID Connect Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>OIDC</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The OpenID Connect standard specifies how a Relying Party (RP) can
      discover metadata about an OpenID Provider (OP), and then register to
      obtain relying party credentials. The discovery and registration process
      does not involve any mechanisms of dynamically establishing trust in the
      exchanged information, but instead rely on-out-of band trust
      establishment.</t>

      <t>In an identity federation context, this is not sufficient. The
      participants of the federation must be able to trust information
      provided about other participants in the federation. OpenID Connect
      Federations specifies how trust can be dynamically obtained from
      resolving trust from a common trusted third party.</t>

      <t>While this specification is primarily targeting OpenID Connect, it is
      designed in order to allow for re-use by other protocols and in other
      use cases.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This specification describes how two entities that would like to
      interact can dynamically fetch and and resolve trust and metadata for a
      given protocol, by the use of third party trust issuers.</t>

      <t>An identity federation can be realized using this specification by
      the use of one or more levels of trust issuers. A trust issuer is an
      entity, which main purpose is to issue trust statements about entities,
      such as OpenID relying party and providers. This specification does not
      mandates a specific way or restrict how a federation may be built.
      Instead the specification provides the basic technical trust
      infrastructure building blocks needed to build a a dynamic and
      distributed trust network such as a federation.</t>

      <t>An entity will typically configure a local trust root to include the
      identifier and the certificate of a the trusted third party &ndash; the
      federation. All entities involved in OpenID Connect Federation,
      including the trust issuers, will have their own unique identifier. This
      identifier is used to dynamically fetch entity statements. As a complete
      chain of entity statements is obtained, connecting the local trust root
      to the target entity, the entity may resolve the resulting trusted
      metadata, by flattening the metadata found in the trust chain.</t>

      <t>Note that a real-world entity like an organisation, a company may be
      represented by more than one entity in a federation.</t>

      <t>The OpenID Connect Federation trust chains are relying on
      cryptographically signed JWT documents, and the trust chain does not at
      all rely on TLS in order to establish trust.</t>

      <t>OpenID Connect Federation may very well be used for other purposes
      than building traditional identity federations. One of them could be to
      build an OpenID Connect deployment where the key rollover process does
      not fall back to TLS. Another could be allowing traditionally
      public/native clients, such as medical devices, to generate its own key
      pair, and use asymmetric crypto to increase the overall security.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="entity-statement" title="Entity Statement ">
      <t>An entity statement is always a signed JWT. An entity statement is
      issued by the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx>, and the statement
      considers the subject entity, the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>. To be
      able to resolve trust and metadata, one needs to know the identifier of
      the target entity &ndash; we refer to this as the leaf entity. The leaf
      entity will always sign a statement about itself, and give some hints to
      other entities that may want to issue statements about itself. All other
      entities in a trust chain we refer to as intermediate entities. The
      local configured trust root, we refer to as the trust anchor.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="iss">REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the entity that
          issues the statement. If the iss and the sub are identical, the
          issuer is making a statement about itself.</t>

          <t hangText="sub">REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the subject</t>

          <t hangText="iat">REQUIRED. The time the statement was issued.</t>

          <t hangText="exp">REQUIRED. The time the signed statement
          expires.</t>

          <t hangText="jwks">REQUIRED. A <xref target="RFC7517">JSON Web Key
          Set (JWKS) </xref> representing the public part of the subject
          entity's signing keys.<vspace blankLines="1"/>These keys are used
          verify the identity of the subject. A corresponding private key is
          used by the leaf entity to sign an entity statement about itself,
          and intermediate entities to sign statements about other entities.
          The keys that can be found here are primarily intended to sign entity
          statements, and can not be used in other protocols, unless the
          metadata type specification explicitly states how the keys can be
          used. In OpenID Connect, the jwks keys cannot be used within the
          Authorization/AccessToken/RefreshToken/UserInfo requests and
          responses. Instead OpenID Connect specific metadata includes claims
          for this purpose.</t>

          <t hangText="authority_hints">OPTIONAL. A JSON object where the keys
          are the intermediate entities that may issue an entity statement
          about the issuer entity. The value MUST be a JSON array of entities
          that is further up in the trust chain. The array may be an empty
          list. The JSON array can be used to simplify the selection of trust
          chains without the need for fetching all possible authority
          hints.</t>

          <t hangText="metadata">REQUIRED. JSON object including protocol
          specific metadata claims that represent the leaf node. To resolve
          the resulting metadata for a leaf node, the compound metadata
          documents included in the trust chain is merged by the <xref
          target="flattening-metadata">metadata flattening process</xref>. The
          keys of the JSON object represent the metadata type identifier, and
          the value MUST be a JSON object representing the metadata according
          to the metadata schema of that metadata type. To allow for the leaf
          node to resolve a specific metadata type, all intermediate entities
          in the trust chain MUST contain a metadata document for this
          specific type. See <xref target="metadata">section about
          metadata</xref>. An entity statement may contain multiple metadata
          statement, but only one for each metadata type.</t>

          <t hangText="sub_is_leaf">OPTIONAL. Boolean value that indicates
          whether the subject is considered a leaf node. A leaf node is not
          trusted to issue statements about other entities than itself. If
          this property is left out, it is considered to be <spanx
          style="verb">false</spanx>.</t>

          <t hangText="sub_meta">OPTIONAL. If present, an JSON object
          containing one or more of the properties listed below. This is
          metadata describing the subject of this entity statement. The
          metadata included in the metadata claim is always referring to the
          leaf nodes, while the metadata in sub_meta refers to the immediate
          subject, which may be an intermediate trust issuer.<vspace
          blankLines="1"/><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="name">OPTIONAL. String. The human readable name
              describing the subject entity. This may be, for example, the name
              of an organization.</t>

              <t hangText="contacts">OPTIONAL. JSON array with one or more
              strings. Contact persons at the entity.</t>

              <t hangText="policy_url">OPTIONAL. URL to documentation of
              conditions and policies relevant to this entity</t>

              <t hangText="homepage_url">OPTIONAL. URL to a generic home page
              representing this entity.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The entity statement is signed using the private key of the issuer
      entity, in the form of a <xref target="RFC7515">JSON Web Signature
      (JWS)</xref>.</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble>Non-normative example of a entity statement, before
        serialization and adding a signature.</preamble>

        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "iss": "https://feide.no",
  "sub": "https://ntnu.no",
  "iat": 1516239022,
  "exp": 1516298022,
  "metadata": {
    "openid_provider": {
      "issuer": "https://ntnu.no",
      "organization": "NTNU",
      "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256", "RS384",
                                                "RS512"]
    },
    "openid_client": {
      "organization": "NTNU",
      "grant_types_supported": ["authorization_code", "implicit"],
      "scopes": ["openid", "profile", "email", "phone"]
    }
  },
  "jwks": {
    "keys": [
      {
        "alg": "RS256",
        "e": "AQAB",
        "ext": true,
        "key_ops": ["verify"],
        "kid": "key1",
        "kty": "RSA",
        "n": "pnXBOusEANuug6ewezb9J_...",
        "use": "sig"
      }
    ]
  },
  "authority_hints": {
    "https://edugain.org/federation": []
  }
}]]></artwork>

        <postamble>(postamble)</postamble>
      </figure>

      <section title="The trust anchor">
        <t>In order to configure trust when deploying a software component, it
        is recommended to align the configuration with the semantics of a
        entity statement. How the configuration is stored and the exact format
        is out of the scope of this specification, but it is recommended to
        allow the user to configure a list of entries containing <spanx
        style="verb">sub</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">jwks</spanx> and <spanx
        style="verb">metadata</spanx>. When the compound metadata from the
        trust chain is resolved, metadata from the local trust root can be
        applied in the <xref target="flattening-metadata">metadata flattening
        process</xref>. This allows the configuration of a provider to put
        trust limitations applied to all metadata resolved for the various
        trust roots. For example, a provider may trust a large federation with
        a metadata limitation of only releasing the name and userid, and no
        other scopes or claims. The provider may add other trust roots with a
        more limited target group to allow for more scopes and claims.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="metadata" title="Metadata">
      <t>The OpenID Connect Federations specification does allow new metadata
      types to be defined, to support use cases outside OpenID Connect. The
      metadata type identifier will uniquely identify which metadata
      specification to interpret.</t>

      <t>The metadata document MUST be a JSON document. Beyond that there is
      no restriction.</t>

      <t>Metadata used in OpenID Connect Federations typically re-uses existing
      metadata standards. If needed, the metadata schema is extended
      with additional properties relevant in a federated context.</t>

      <section title="OpenID Connect Relying Party Metadata">
        <t>The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid_client</spanx>.</t>

        <t>All parameters defined in section 2 of <xref
        target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client
        Registration 1.0</xref> are allowed in a metadata statement.</t>

        <t>To that list is added: <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="allowed_scopes"><vspace/>RECOMMENDED. JSON array
            containing a list of the <xref target="RFC6749">RFC6749</xref>
            scope values that this relying party expects to use.</t>

            <t hangText="allowed_claims"><vspace/>RECOMMENDED. JSON array
            containing a list of the Claim Names of the Claims that the OpenID
            Client wants values for.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="OpenID Provider Metadata">
        <t>The metadata type identifier is an
          <spanx style="verb">openid_provider</spanx>.</t>

        <t>All parameters defined in section 3 of <xref
        target="OpenID.Discovery">OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</xref></t>

        <t>In addition the following properties are allowed:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="organizationName"><vspace/>OPTIONAL. A human readable
            name representing the organization owning the OpenID Provider. It
            is intended to be used in the user interface, being recognized by
            the end users that would be using the provider to
            authenticate.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="OpenID Connect Discovery">
        <t>The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid-discovery</spanx>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="OAuth Provider">
        <t>The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid-provider</spanx>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="OAuth Client">
        <t>The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid_client</spanx>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="OAuth Protected Resources">
        <t>The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid-api</spanx>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Federation API">
      <t>Given the entity identifier, the endpoint of the federation API
      endpoint of the entity is easily derived. All entities that are expected
      to expose entity statements about themselves or other entities, MUST
      implement a Federation API.</t>

      <t>The federation API endpoint of an entity, is resolved from the entity
      identifier. The Federation API endpoint is found using the <xref
      target="RFC5785">Well known URIs</xref> specification, with the suffix
      <spanx style="verb">openid-federation</spanx>. The scheme, host and port
      is taken directly from the entity identifier combined with the following
      path: <spanx style="verb">/.well-known/openid-federation</spanx>.</t>

      <t>The Federation API is an HTTP API that may support multiple
      operations. Fetching entities is one of the operations, and the only one
      that all entities is REQUIRED to support. All the other operations is
      OPTIONAL. The <spanx style="verb">op</spanx> (operation) parameter may
      be used to defined new operations in a future version of the
      specification or a local deployment which have agreed upon additional
      functionality.</t>

      <t>While all operations in the specification make use of a GET request,
      other operations may choose to use other HTTP methods. If the <spanx
      style="verb">op</spanx> parameter is left out, it is considered to be a
      fetch entity statements request. Unless otherwise mentioned or agreed
      upon, requests to the federation API does not need to be
      authenticated.</t>

      <section title="Fetching entity statements (REQUIRED)">
        <t>Fetching entity statements is used to collect entity statements and
        a valid trust chain in order to establish trust with a remote
        peer.</t>

        <t>In order to fetch entity statements, you need to know the
        identifier of the entity to ask, and the identifier of the entity that
        you want the statement to be about. Typically the first entity
        statement to fetch is the remote peer self issued entity
        statement.</t>

        <section title="Fetch Entity Statements Request">
          <t>The request MUST be a HTTP request using the GET method to a
          resolved federation API endpoint with the following query string
          parameters:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="op">OPTIONAL. If not present MUST be set to <spanx
              style="verb">fetch</spanx>.</t>

              <t hangText="iss">REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the issuer
              from which you want an entity statement issued. Because of the
              normalization of the URL, multiple issuers may resolve to a
              shared federation API. This parameter makes it explicit exactly
              which issuer we want entity statements from.</t>

              <t hangText="sub">OPTIONAL. The entity identifier of the subject
              for which you would like an entity statement issued. If this
              parameter is left out, it is considered to be the same as the
              issuer, and would indicate a request for a self issued
              statement.</t>

              <t hangText="aud">OPTIONAL. The entity identifier of the
              requester. The issuing entity may choose to include this
              parameter to form the entity statement specifically for this
              target, in which the <spanx style="verb">aud</spanx> claim also
              should be present in the entity statement it self.</t>

              <t hangText="prefetch">OPTIONAL. If left out, it is assumed to
              be <spanx style="verb">false</spanx>. If set to <spanx
              style="verb">true</spanx>, it indicates that the requester would
              like the API to prefetch entity statements that may be relevant
              for consumer to establish a trust chain, and may save the
              consumer from performing additional API requests.</t>
            </list></t>

          <figure>
            <preamble>The following is a non-normative example of an API
            request for entity statement:</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /.well-known/openid-federation?
iss=https%3A%2F%2Fopenid.sunet.se%2Ffederation HTTP/1.1
Host: openid.sunet.se
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>(postamble)</postamble>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Fetch Entity Statements Response">
          <t>As long as the request is correct, understood and accepted, the
          response MUST be a JSON array including signed entity statements.
          The content type MUST be set to <spanx style="verb">application/json</spanx>.
          If the issuing entity does not recognize the subject or the issuer,
          it should return an empty JSON array. The returned list of entity
          statements SHOULD include a statement issued by the issuing entity
          about the entity represented in the subject parameter. The issuing
          entity may also decide to prefetch additional entity statements that
          may be relevant to the requester.</t>

          <figure>
            <preamble>A non-normative example of a response:</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[200 OK
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

["eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJodHRwczovL3Nlc..."]
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>(the signed JWT is truncated)</postamble>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Trust negotiation (OPTIONAL)">
        <t>An entity may use the trust negotiation operation in order to fetch
        a resolved metadata of it self as seen/trusted by a remote peer. The
        remote peer will fetch the metadata and necessary trust chain to the
        requester, and perform metadata flattening. The remote peer should
        include it own trust root configuration when generating the resulting
        metadata. The metadata returned should be the same as the one used in
        the software.</t>

        <section title="Trust negotiation Request">
          <t>Resolving metadata for a specific type of metadata, for a given
          peer. The relying party may ask a specific provider to resolve the
          relying party openid_client metadata with its own configured trust
          root. The result may tell what operations, scopes and claims the
          relying party is allowed to use.</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="op">REQUIRED. MUST be set to
                <spanx style="verb">resolve_metadata</spanx>.</t>

              <t hangText="iss">REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the issuer
              from which you want to resolve metadata. Because of the
              normalization of the URL, multiple issuers may resolve to a
              shared federation API. This parameter makes it expicit exactly
              which issuer we want to interact with.</t>

              <t hangText="peer">REQUIRED. The entity identifeir of the .</t>

              <t hangText="type">REQUIRED. The metadata type to resolve.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Trust negotiation Response">
          <t>The response is a generated flattened metadata of the type
          specified in the request.</t>

          <figure>
            <preamble>A non-normative example of a response:</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[200 OK
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "organization": "University of Ume?",
  "contacts": ["legal@umu.se", "technical@umu.se"],
  "logo_uri":
    "https://www.umu.se/SRWStatic/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
  "policy_uri":
    "https://www.umu.se/en/about-the-website/legal-information/",
  "authorization_endpoint":
    "https://idp.umu.se/openid/authorization",
  "token_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/token",
  "response_types_supported": ["code", "code id_token", "token"],
  "grant_types_supported": [
    "authorization_code",
    "implicit",
    "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
  ],
  "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise"],
  "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256"],
  "LoaMax": "http://swamid.se/LoA/substantial",
  "expires": 8776635
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Entity listings (OPTIONAL)">
        <t>An entity may query another entity for a list of all
        entities that that entity is prepared to issue statements about.</t>

        <section title="Entity Listings Request">
          <t>The following request parameters are allowed in the query part:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="op">REQUIRED. MUST be set to
                <spanx style="verb">listing</spanx>.</t>

              <t hangText="iss">REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the issuer
              from which you want to resolve metadata. Because of the
              normalization of the URL, multiple issuers may resolve to a
              shared federation API. This parameter makes it expicit exactly
              which issuer we want to interact with.</t>

              <t hangText="type">OPTIONAL. Provide this parameter to filter
              the results to entity statements that contain entries for this
              specific metadata type.</t>

              <t hangText="sub_is_leaf">OPTIONAL. If left out, result should
              include both leaf nodes and intermediate nodes. If set to true,
              the response should contain only leaf nodes. If set to true, the
              response should contain only intermediate nodes.</t>

              <t hangText="claims">OPTIONAL. A comma separated list of claim
              names that the requester would like to get for each entity. If
              left out or an empty string, the response should contain an
              empty object for each of the known entities.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Entity Listing Response">
          <t>The response MUST contain an JSON object where the known entity
          identifiers are the propery keys, and a JSON object with the
          requested claims is the property value. Requested claims that the
          responder is not able to provide should be left out.</t>

          <figure>
            <preamble>A non-normative example of a response:</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[200 OK
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "https://ntnu.andreas.labs.uninett.no/": {
    "client_name": "NTNU Labs"
  },
  "https://blackboard.ntnu.no/openid/callback": {
    "client_name": "Blackboard"
  },
  "https://serviceprovider.andreas.labs.uninett.no/application1007": {
    "client_name": "Test application"
  }
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Force refreshing of entity statements">
        <t>TBD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Generic Error Response">
        <t>If the request was malformed, or some error occured during
        processing of the request, the following standardized error format
        should be used regardless of the operation specified.</t>

        <t>The HTTP response code MUST be something else than 200, giving an
        indication of the type of error. The response body MUST be a JSON
        object including these claims:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="op">REQUIRED. Which operation was the request
            processed as.</t>

            <t hangText="error">REQUIRED. Shor text tag indicating the error
            code.</t>

            <t hangText="error_description">REQUIRED. A human readable short
            text describing the error.</t>
          </list></t>

        <figure>
          <preamble>A non-normative example of a error response:</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[200 Invalid request
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "op": "fetch",
  "error": "generic_error",
  "error_description":
    "Required request parameter [iss] was missing."
}
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>(the signed JWT is truntated)</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="resolving_trust"
             title="Resolving trust chain and metadata">
      <t>An entity seeking to establish trust with a remote peer will start
      with the knowledge of the remote peer entity identifier and with a
      locally configured trust anchor. The entity will first have to fetch
      sufficient entity statements to establish a chain of trust from the
      remote peer to the locally configured trust anchor. Afterwards, the
      seeking entity will have to validate the trust chain and choose one if
      there are multiple valid trust chains.</t>

      <section anchor="fetching-es"
               title="Fetching entity statements to establish a trust chain">
        <t>The seeking entity should always start to ask the remote peer
        entity about its self-issued entity statement. This entity statement
        MAY contain an list of intermediate entities in the authority_hints
        claim.</t>

        <t>The seeking entity may iterate through the list of authority_hints
        and request an entity statement on the remote peer from each of the
        intermediates. It may further iterate intermediate entity statements
        for their authority_hints, and so on. The seeking entity should never
        attempt to fetch entity statements that it has already fetched in this
        process (loop prevention).</t>

        <t>The result of this operation should be a number of flat lists of
        entity statements.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Finding trust chains">
        <t>The seeking entity will look for paths from the remote peer entity
        to the locally configured trust anchors. If no path is found, the
        process of establishing trust has failed. The result may also very
        well be more than one possible path.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Validating the trust chains">
        <t>A trust chain consists of an ordered list of entity statements that
        refer to each other from one entry in the local trust anchor to the
        self-issued entity statement of the remote peer.</t>

        <t>We refer to the locally configured trust root as ES0, the top level
        intermediate entity statement as ES1, up to the self signed entity
        statement ESi. A trust chain without any intermediate entities is also
        valid. The trust anchor might include a ES0 representing a direct
        trust to a remote peer, and the self-issued statement of the peer will
        then be ES1.</t>

        <t>To validate the chain, the signed JWT ES1 is validated against the
        public signing keys in ES0, jwks. Next, the signed JWT ES2 is
        validated against the public signing keys in ES1, and so on until the
        complete chain is validated.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Choosing one of the valid trust chains">
        <t>If multiple valid trust chain is found, the seeking entity will
        need to decide</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trust_lifetime"
               title="Calculating the lifetime of a trust chain">
        <t>Each entity statement in a trust chain is signed and MUST have a
        expiration time (exp) set. Given that all of them are sometime in the
        future then the expiration time of the whole trust chain is then the
        expiration time that is closest in time to the present time.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Updating metadata, key-rollover and revocation">
      <t>The OpenID Connect Federation allows for a smooth process of updating
      metadata and public keys.</t>

      <t>Each entity statement has an explicit expiration time. A trust chain
      is valid until one or more of the involved entity statements expires.
      This specification describes how entity statement is fetched and
      metadata is resolved for the first time, but a consumer of metadata from
      OpenID Connect Federation MUST support refreshing at least the expired
      entity statements and re-evaluate the whole trust chain when needed.</t>

      <t>Setting an expiration time on an entity statement can be used to
      control how often the remote party is fetching an updated version of
      your public key.</t>

      <section title="Leaf node key-rollover on keys used in protocol">
        <t>A leaf node, such as an OpenID Provider will typically have at
        least two set of key pairs, one that is embedded in the entity
        statement issued by the superior trust issuer, and one that is
        embedded in the protocol specific metadata that is included in the
        self issuer entity statement.</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Generate a new key pair to use K2 to replace the existing K1.
            The lifetime T1 is the time until all previously issued entity
            statements are expired.</t>

            <t>Publish both K1 and K2 in the self issued entity statement. Use
            K1 to sign outgoing messages. Accept encrypted messages to both K1
            and K2. Set K2 to prioritized key. Wait at least T1 before moving
            to next step.</t>

            <t>Remove K1 from published entity statements. Start signing
            outgoing messages with K2, accept incoming encrypted messages with
            both K1 and K2. Wait at least T1.</t>

            <t>Only K2 is used and accepted.</t>
          </list>The complete time of this key-rollover process is 2x T1.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Key-rollover for entity signing key">
        <t>Identical to the section above, but the entity statements is issued
        by the superior party, such that an out of band process for the entity
        to push its key material to the superior entity MUST be added.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Key rollover for trust roots">
        <t>As previous steps.</t>

        <t>Take into considerations that clients have manually configured
        pubic keys as part of configuration.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Updating metadata">
        <t>The process of updating its own metadata follows the same procedure
        as with public keys.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Revocation">
        <t/>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="flattening-metadata"
             title="Flattening metadata from the chain of entity statements">
      <t>The metadata for a specific entity can be constructed by starting
      with the information in ms_0 and then adding the information in ms_1 to
      ms_n using the following rule:</t>

      <t>Given two metadata statements ms_i and ms_j (j &gt; i, i=0, ..., n-1,
      j=1, ..., n) For every claim in ms_j: If the claim does not appear in
      ms_i add it to ms_i. If the claim appears in ms_i then replace the value
      of the claim in ms_i with the value of the claim in ms_j if and only if
      the value in ms_j is a subset of the value in ms_i else an error MUST be
      generated.</t>

      <t>A subset is defined as: <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="String"><vspace/> One string is a subset of another
          string if it is exactly the same, byte by byte.</t>

          <t hangText="Simple lists"><vspace/> An array A is a subset of B if
          every element in A is also in B. And if of the matching elements the
          one in A is a subset of the one in B.</t>

          <t hangText="Booleans"><vspace/> Boolean A is a subset of B if A is
          equal to B.</t>

          <t hangText="Integer/Floats"><vspace/> The number A is a subset of
          the number B if A is less or equal to B.</t>

          <t hangText="Associative array/dictionary"><vspace/> The dictionary A
          is a subset of the dictionary B if every key in A is in B and the
          value of A[x] is a subset of B[x].</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The following is a non-normative example of a set of relying
      party-specific metadata statements that together form the metadata for
      an entity: <figure>
          <preamble>ms_0</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "contacts": ["helpdesk@example.com"],
  "logo_uri": "https://example.com/logo.jpg",
  "policy_uri": "https://example.com/policy.html",
  "tos_uri": "https://example.com/tos.html"
}
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure> <figure>
          <preamble>ms_1</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "rp_scopes": ["openid", "eduperson"],
  "response_types": ["code", "code id_token"],
}
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure> <figure>
          <preamble>ms_2</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "contacts": ["rp_helpdesk@example.com"],
  "redirect_uris": ["https://example.com/rp1"],
  "response_types: ["code"]
}            ]]></artwork>
        </figure> The metadata for the entity in question, using the rules
      above, would then be: <figure>
          <preamble>sum(ms_0...2)</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "contacts": ["helpdesk@example.com"],
  "logo_uri": "https://example.com/logo.jpg",
  "policy_uri": "https://example.com/policy.html",
  "tos_uri": "https://example.com/tos.html"
  "rp_scopes": ["openid", "eduperson"],
  "response_types": ["code"],
  "redirect_uris": ["https://example.com/rp1"],
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="OpenID Connect Communication">
      <t>This section describes how the trust framework in this specification
      is used to establish trust between an OpenID Relying Party and an OpenID
      Provider that has no explicit configuration or registration in advance.
      The use of OpenID Connect Federation enables dynamically building large
      scale multi-lateral federations.</t>

      <t>There are two alternative approaches to establish trust between a
      Relying Party and a Provider. Members of a federation or a community
      should agree upon which approach to use. Whilst implementations should
      support both methods, deployments may choose to disable the use of one
      of them.</t>

      <section title="Explicit Registration">
        <t>This method involves performing an explicit registration of a new
        client the first time a Relying Party interacts with an OpenID
        Provider using something akin to <xref
        target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client
        Registration 1.0</xref>.</t>

        <t>It is assumed that a federation entity has a set of
        authority_hints and knowledge about which trust anchor that can be
        found at the end of a trust chain starting in each authorityHint. How
        the entity has received this knowledge is outside the scope of this
        document.</t>

        <section title="Provider Discovery">
          <t>The RP will start by figuring out the OPs metadata using the
          process specified in <xref target="resolving_trust">Resolving trust
          chain and metadata </xref> above.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Clireg" title="Client Registration">
          <section anchor="Cliregreq" title="Client Registration Request">
            <t>The OP MUST support dynamic relying party registration. That it
            does so is signaled by having the claim
              <spanx style="verb">federation_registration_endpoint</spanx> in the metadata.</t>

            <t>Given that the OP supports dynamic registration the RP
            progresses as follows: <list style="numbers">
                <t>Once it has the list of acceptable trust chains for the OP
                it MUST choose the subset it wants to progress with. The
                subset can be as small as one trust chain but it can also
                contain more then one.</t>

                <t>Based on the trust anchors referenced in the subset of
                trust chains, the RP will choose a set of authority_hints from
                its own set that terminates in those trust anchors.</t>

                <t>The RP will now construct a self-signed entity statement
                where the metadata statement chosen is influenced by the OPs
                metadata and the authority_hints specified are picked by the
                process described above.</t>

                <t>The entity statement is sent to the
                  <spanx style="verb">federation_registration_endpoint</spanx> defined in this document.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="cliregresp" title="Client Registration Response">
            <t>Now on the OPs side the following occurs: <list style="number">
                <t>It receives the request, collects and evaluates the trust
                chains starting with the authority_hints in the registration
                request. After having verified such chains it can verify that
                the signature on the received registration request is
                correct.</t>

                <t>If it finds more than one acceptable trust chain it MUST
                choose one or more that terminates in one and the same trust
                anchor.</t>

                <t>At this point, if there already exists a client
                registration under the same entity_id then that registration
                MUST be regarded as invalid.</t>

                <t>The OP will now construct an entity statement containing a
                description of the RPs metadata that the OP finds acceptable.
                To the entity statement it will add one or more
                authority_hints from its collection, that terminates in the
                trust anchor chosen above.</t>

                <t>It will sign and return the signed entity statement to the
                RP</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Back at the RP it will: <list style="number">
                <t>Verify the correctness of the received entity statement.
                Making sure that the trust chains starting at the
                authority_hints terminates in trust anchors that where
                referenced in the entity statement it sent to the OP.</t>

                <t>If the RP is OK with the metadata that was the result of
                the flattening of the received entity statement then it stores
                the configuration and can continue communicating with the OP
                using the agreed on metadata.</t>

                <t>If the RP was not OK, for some reason, with the received
                entity statement then it has the choice to restart the
                registration process or to give up.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="After client registration">
          <t>A client registration using this specification is not expected to
          be valid for ever. The entity statements exchanged all have
          expiration times, which means that the registration will eventually
          time out. An OP can also for some reason decide that a client
          registration is not valid anymore. To this can be added that the
          entities in the federation, for a number of reasons, over time may
          change how fast their signature will expire, thereby increasing or
          decreasing the lifetime of a trust chain.</t>

          <section title="What the RP MUST do">
            <t>At regular intervals the RP MUST: <list style="number">
                <t>Starting with the OPs entity statement, resolve and verify
                the trust chains it chose to use when constructing the
                registration request. If those trust chains don't exist
                anymore or do not verify, then the registration should be
                regarded as invalid and a new registration process should be
                started.</t>

                <t>If the OPs entity statement was OK it must now verify that
                the entity statement it received about itself from the OP is
                still valid. Again, if that is not the case the registration
                should be regarded as invalid and a new registration process
                should be started.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="What the OP MUST do">
            <t/>TBD
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Implicit Registration">
        <t/>

        <figure>
          <preamble>The trust between the entities is established using the
          above described extensions in the first two steps of the
          communication between an RP and an OP. How the RP found the OP in
          the first place is out of scope for this document.</preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[------                                       ------
|    | <--- 1) Discovery ------------------> |    |
| RP | ---- 2) Authentication request -----> | OP |
|    |                                       |    |
------                                       ------     ]]></artwork>

          <postamble>After the discovery and registration is completed a first
          time, those steps SHOULD only be repeated if any changes occur (see
          notes in respective sections below).</postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>The client_id of the RP MUST be set identical to the RP entity
        identifier.</t>

        <t>Without a registration process, the RP does not have any
        client_secret. Instead the implicit registration model requires the RP
        to make use of asymmetric crypto.</t>

        <t>The RP MUST host a Federation API that allows the OP to fetch the
        entity statements.</t>

        <section title="The Authentication Request">
          <t>The authentication request as specified in OpenID Connect
          Core.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Processing the authentication request">
          <t>When the OP receives an incoming authentication request and both
          the OP supports OpenID Connect Federation and the incoming client_id
          is a valid URL, the OP should try to resolve and fetch the entity
          statement as described in <xref target="fetching-es">fetching entity
          statements</xref>.</t>

          <t>The OP should validate the possible trust chains, and resolve the
          RP metadata with type <spanx style="verb">openid_client</spanx>.</t>

          <t>The OP should consider the resolved metadata of the RP and
          perform these additional validation steps:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Verify that the metadata contains a public key... TODO: add
              proper reference.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authentication Error Response">
          <t>If the OP fails to establish trust with the RP, it should use the
          <spanx style="verb">error_description</spanx> error code, with an
          <spanx style="verb">error_description</spanx> that aids the RP to
          fix what is wrong.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authentication at the Token endpoint">
          <t>The RP will have to use asymmetric crypto to authenticate to the
          token endpoint. The RP MUST authenticate the request by including
          the <spanx style="verb">private_key_jwt</spanx> parameter, as
          described in OpenID Connect Core Section 9.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Timeouts">
      <t>There are a number of timeouts that MUST considered: <list
          style="empty">
          <t>Each signature has a timeout.</t>

          <t>A relying party registration has a timeout.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Taking this into consideration, an OP MUST NOT assign a lifetime to a
      relying party registration that exceeds the lifetime of the metadata
      statement signatures.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Heather Flanagan</t>

          <t>The JRA3T3 task force of GEANT4-2</t>

          <t>Michael Schwartz</t>

          <t>Peter Schober</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7515"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5785"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7517"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6962"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7033"?>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Core"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
            Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B."
                  surname="de Medeiros">
            <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
            <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="3" month="August" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Discovery"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-discovery-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
            Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Edmund Jay" initials="E." surname="Jay">
            <organization abbrev="Illumila">Illumila</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="3" month="August" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Registration"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-registration-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
            Ltd.</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="3" month="August" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Illustrative example of OpenID Connect flow">
      <t>A service Foodle would like to offer its services to all identity
      providers in eduGAIN. Foodle is managed and registered by the university
      NTNU. NTNU is part of the Norwegian Feide federation. Foodle is also
      directly trusted in the Swedish SWAMID federation. Both Feide and SWAMID
      are part of the international eduGAIN federation.</t>

      <section title="Initial setup of Foodle">
        <t>The Foodle service choose to use the entity identifier <spanx
        style="verb">https://foodl.org/</spanx>. And upon deployment, Foodle
        is setup with a RSA keypair, with the following public key:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "kid": "key1",
  "use": "sig",
  "kty": "RSA",
  "alg": "RS256",
  "n": "pnXBOusEANuug6ewezb9J_XbxbSGEISyA75wBGkerPNg6WTXmmxJ-DV1U4sCu
RqhSdo3Uncmw6-01bZKCtAyRHT_TOZN2TMfNPRsfLkOstVofyfxg5oIWViLX9IDG_iZVd
q6_T6yOuufOIvqpaeBMwSKuDXHNa_DU0aUu_3kOAc5_2hD4Dq-XXtum-oix2EPkNSbFfP
qFIp5n4gS1XrzGzuNQiDw82k-H6mWN0wlVWfqLxJA9DZikAX7x9feipn36wxDH-XUlzDD
Ui3nfnC8GSkT-CYII3oZPsIgMV527iQGVsehIV9KqTF2FnaP83cqV9YgvMfhs1wrx4L3Z
-3B8Q",
  "e": "AQAB",
  "key_ops": ["verify"],
  "ext": true
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Foodle offers a WebFinger interface and a metadata API according to
        this specification, with the ability to issue entity statements about
        itself.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Federation setup">
        <t>How trust is established and entities becomes part of a federation
        is out of scope of this specification. But it could involve some kind
        of non-technical contract, agreement or term of use that is
        established, followed by a federation or trust issuer that registers
        an entity identifier, public key and a set of metadata that restricts
        the delegated trust that is represented in the entity statement about
        the joining party.</t>

        <t>The following example, assumes the following trust relations is
        established, and the following entities are able to issue entity
        statements:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Foodle issues an entity statement about it self</t>

            <t>NTNU issues an entity statement about Foodle</t>

            <t>SWAMID issues an entity statement about Foodle</t>

            <t>Feide issues an entity statement about NTNU</t>

            <t>eduGAIN issues an entity statement about Feide</t>

            <t>eduGAIN issues an entity statement about SWAMID</t>

            <t>SWAMID issues an entity statement about the university of Umea
            - an OpenID provider for employees and students at the university
            of Umea</t>
          </list>Foodle has a local trust root configuration that looks like
        this (notice that the exact format and content on the trust root
        configuration is out of scope of this specification):</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[[
  {
    "sub": "https://www.sunet.se/swamid",
    "sub_meta": {"name": "SWAMID"},
    "metadata": {
      "openid-provider": {"loa_max": "http://swamid.se/LoA/substantial"}
    },
    "jwks": {
      "keys": [
        {
          "kty": "RSA",
          "alg": "RS256",
          "n": "v6xydqciFKGfvQaqYGmk9A7etbfvNY[...]",
          "e": "AQAB",
          "key_ops": ["verify"],
          "ext": true,
          "kid": "swamid",
          "use": "sig"
        }
      ]
    }
  }
]]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="User choose to login at Foodle">
        <t>Let us assume a student from Ume&aring; would like to login at
        Foodle. Some sort of discovery process involves the end user choosing
        an OpenID provider. OpenID Discovery using the e-mail address is one
        option. Foodle presenting a list of available providers for the user
        to choose from is another.</t>

        <t>After the discovery process, Foodle knows that the user would like
        to login using the OpenID provider with entity identifier <spanx
        style="verb">https://www.umu.se/openid</spanx>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Foodle discovers the OpenID provider">
        <t>Foodle normalizes the entity identifier of the OpenID Provider, and
        performs a request to fetch the self issued entity statement using the
        federation API of the OpenID provider.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /.well-known/openid-federation?
iss=https%3A%2F%2Fumu.se%2Fopenid HTTP/1.1
Host: umu.se]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json
["eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCIsImtpZCI6InVtdSJ9.eyJpYXQiOjE1..."]]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The API endpoint returns a list of signed entity statements. In
        this case we look for a selfissued statement from the Ume&aring;
        university. We then decode and inspect the content:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "iat": 1539174048,
  "exp": 1539177648,
  "metadata": {
    "openid-provider": {
      "authorization_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/authorization",
      "token_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/token",
      "response_types_supported": ["code", "code id_token", "token"],
      "grant_types_supported": [
        "authorization_code",
        "implicit",
        "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
      ],
      "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise", "public"],
      "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256"],
      "logo_uri":
        "https://www.umu.se/SRWStatic/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
      "policy_uri":
        "https://www.umu.se/en/about-the-website/legal-information/",
      "loa_max": "http://eidas.europa.eu/LoA/high"
    }
  },
  "iss": "https://umu.se/openid",
  "sub": "https://umu.se/openid",
  "authority_hints": {
    "https://www.sunet.se/swamid": ["https://edugain.org/oidc"],
    "https://kalmar2.org/openid": []
  },
  "jwks": {
    "keys": [
      {
        "kty": "RSA",
        "alg": "RS256",
        "n": "z1V1kyi6qwmXfKsfhVqKUMmQH3AixN[...]",
        "e": "AQAB",
        "key_ops": ["verify"],
        "ext": true,
        "kid": "umu",
        "use": "sig"
      }
    ]
  }
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Resolving the provider trust chain">
        <t>In order to establish trust with this provider, the Foodle service
        provider would need to fetch sufficient entity statements to represent
        a complete chain from the self issued statement to the locally
        configured trust root, which contain SWAMID.</t>

        <t>The information found in the authority_hints is critical in order
        to dynamically discover the trust chain. If such hints are not
        present, the relying party may resume to fixed configured trust roots
        to ask for trust statements.</t>

        <t>In this example, Foodle now fetches an entity statement from SWAMID
        using the federation API endpoint of SWAMID, discovered in the
        authority_hints claim.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /.well-known/openid-federation?
iss=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.sunet.se%2Fswamid&
sub=https%3A%2F%2Fumu.se%2Fopenid HTTP/1.1
Host: www.sunet.se]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json
["eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCIsImtpZCI6ImZlaWRlIn0.eyJpYXQi..."]]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The decoded version of the entity statement is:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "iat": 1539174048,
  "exp": 1539177648,
  "metadata": {
    "openid-provider": {
      "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise"],
      "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256", "RS512"],
      "organization": "University of Ume?",
      "contacts": ["legal@umu.se", "technical@umu.se"]
    },
    "openid-client": {}
  },
  "iss": "https://www.sunet.se/swamid",
  "sub": "https://umu.se/openid",
  "sub_meta": {"name": "University of Ume?"},
  "jwks": {
    "keys": [
      {
        "kty": "RSA",
        "alg": "RS256",
        "n": "v6xydqciFKGfvQaqYGmk9A7etbfvNY[...]",
        "e": "AQAB",
        "key_ops": ["verify"],
        "ext": true,
        "kid": "swamid",
        "use": "sig"
      }
    ]
  }
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Notice that the entity statement about University of Ume&aring;
        also contains an entry for openid_client metadata. This indicates that
        SWAMID express this university to be trusted to issue its own OpenID
        clients without the need for registering these directly in SWAMID.</t>

        <t>These two entity statements are sufficient to establish a path from
        the local configured trust anchor which trust SWAMID, to the
        selfissued statement from the University of Ume&aring;. Here are the
        steps performed to validate the trust chain:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Find the trusted public keys for SWAMID in local trust
            configuration.</t>

            <t>Use these keys to validate the signature of the signed entity
            statement issued by SWAMID about the University of Ume&aring;</t>

            <t>Check that the sub from the trust configuration matches the iss
            value of the first entity statement.</t>

            <t>Extract the jwks entry from this entity statement. These are
            the signing keys of the University of Ume&aring;</t>

            <t>Validate the self signed statement from Universy of Ume&aring;
            using the keys found above.</t>

            <t>Check that the sub from the previous statement matches the iss
            of the self issued statement.</t>

            <t>Check that the self issued statement has the iss and sub to be
            the same.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Extracting the provider metadata">
        <t>The output from the trust chain validation is an ordered list of
        entity statements. In order to extract the needed metadata, we need to
        look at the metadata type relevant in the given context. In this case,
        we are establishing trust with an OpenID Provider, and we take a look
        at the <spanx style="varb">openid_provider</spanx> metadata object of
        the trust chain:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[[
  {"loa_max": "http://swamid.se/LoA/substantial"},
  {
    "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise"],
    "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256", "RS512"],
    "organization": "University of Ume?",
    "contacts": ["legal@umu.se", "technical@umu.se"]
  },
  {
    "authorization_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/authorization",
    "token_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/token",
    "response_types_supported": ["code", "code id_token", "token"],
    "grant_types_supported": [
      "authorization_code",
      "implicit",
      "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
    ],
    "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise", "public"],
    "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256"],
    "logo_uri":
      "https://www.umu.se/SRWStatic/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
    "policy_uri":
      "https://www.umu.se/en/about-the-website/legal-information/",
    "loa_max": "http://eidas.europa.eu/LoA/high"
  }
]]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The metadata flattening process converts this to a single metadata
        object. The resulting metadata in this case would be:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "organization": "University of Ume?",
  "contacts": ["legal@umu.se", "technical@umu.se"],
  "logo_uri":
    "https://www.umu.se/SRWStatic/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
  "policy_uri":
    "https://www.umu.se/en/about-the-website/legal-information/",
  "authorization_endpoint":
    "https://idp.umu.se/openid/authorization",
  "token_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/token",
  "response_types_supported": ["code", "code id_token", "token"],
  "grant_types_supported": [
    "authorization_code",
    "implicit",
    "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
  ],
  "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise"],
  "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256"],
  "loa_max": "http://swamid.se/LoA/substantial"
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="RP sends authentication request (implicit registration)">
        <t>Foodle after establishing trust with the University of Ume&aring;
        and extracted a resulting set of metadata, will send an authentication
        request to the OpenID provider. This example involves the implicit
        registration.</t>

        <t>Here is an example of an authentication request:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[GET /authorize?
  response_type=code
  &scope=openid%20profile%20email
  &client_id=https%3A%2F%2Ffoodl.org%2F
  &state=2ff7e589-3848-46da-a3d2-949e1235e671
  &redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Ffoodl.org%2Fopenid%2Fcallback HTTP/1.1
Host: idp.umu.se
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The provider receiving this authentication request, will unless the
        RP is cached or statically configured, start to dynamically fetch and
        establish trust with the RP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Provider fetches entity statements">
        <t>The provider needs to establish a trust chain for RP from which a
        authentication was received. The provider in this example has the
        following configured trust root:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[[
  {
    "sub": "https://edugain.org/oidc",
    "metadata": {
      "openid-client": {
        "rp_scopes": ["openid", "userid-targetedid", "eduperson"],
        "response_types": ["code", "code id_token"]
      }
    },
    "jwks": {
      "keys": [
        {
          "kty": "RSA",
          "use": "sig",
          "alg": "RS256",
          "n": "qnd5_krrHKzuJzb5_YEt4sP-YOGSbf[...]",
          "e": "AQAB",
          "key_ops": ["verify"],
          "ext": true,
          "kid": "edugain"
        }
      ]
    }
  },
  {
    "sub": "https://www.sunet.se/swamid",
    "metadata": {
      "openid-client": {
        "rp_scopes": ["openid", "userid-persistent", "fs"],
        "response_types": ["code", "code id_token"]
      }
    },
    "jwks": {
      "keys": [
        {
          "kty": "RSA",
          "alg": "RS256",
          "n": "v6xydqciFKGfvQaqYGmk9A7etbfvNY[...]",
          "e": "AQAB",
          "key_ops": ["verify"],
          "ext": true,
          "kid": "swamid",
          "use": "sig"
        }
      ]
    }
  }
]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Provider fetches entity statements">
        <t>The provider starts to resolve metadata for the client identifier
        https://foodl.org/ by fetching the self issued entity statement using
        the federation API.</t>

        <t/>

        <t>uses WebFinger, the metadata API endpoints and the authority_hints
        in order to establish a full trust chain to the trust root.</t>

        <t>In this case there are two possible trust chains:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>eduGAIN -&gt; Feide -&gt; NTNU -&gt; Foodle</t>

            <t>SWAMID -&gt; Foodle</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Notices" title="Notices">
      <t>Copyright (c) 2018 The OpenID Foundation.</t>

      <t>The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer,
      implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free,
      worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works from,
      distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or Final
      Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing specifications,
      and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and Final Specifications based
      on such documents, provided that attribution be made to the OIDF as the
      source of the material, but that such attribution does not indicate an
      endorsement by the OIDF.</t>

      <t>The technology described in this specification was made available
      from contributions from various sources, including members of the OpenID
      Foundation and others. Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps to
      help ensure that the technology is available for distribution, it takes
      no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual property
      or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation
      or use of the technology described in this specification or the extent
      to which any license under such rights might or might not be available;
      neither does it represent that it has made any independent effort to
      identify any such rights. The OpenID Foundation and the contributors to
      this specification make no (and hereby expressly disclaim any)
      warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), including implied
      warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, fitness for a
      particular purpose, or title, related to this specification, and the
      entire risk as to implementing this specification is assumed by the
      implementer. The OpenID Intellectual Property Rights policy requires
      contributors to offer a patent promise not to assert certain patent
      claims against other contributors and against implementers. The OpenID
      Foundation invites any interested party to bring to its attention any
      copyrights, patents, patent applications, or other proprietary rights
      that may cover technology that may be required to practice this
      specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="History" title="Document History">
      <t>[[ To be removed from the final specification ]]</t>

      <t>-05 <list style="symbols">
          <t>A major rewrite.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-04 <list style="symbols">
          <t>Changed client metadata names <spanx style="verb">scopes</spanx>
          to <spanx style="verb">rp_scopes</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">claims</spanx>
          to <spanx style="verb">rp_claims</spanx>.</t>

          <t>Added Open Issues appendix.</t>

          <t>Added additional references.</t>

          <t>Editorial improvements.</t>

          <t>Added standard Notices section, which is present in all OpenID
          specifications.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
