<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
        "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  NOTE:  This XML file is input used to produce the authoritative copy of an
  OpenID Foundation specification.  The authoritative copy is the HTML output.
  This XML source file is not authoritative.  The statement ipr="none" is
  present only to satisfy the document compilation tool and is not indicative
  of the IPR status of this specification.  The IPR for this specification is
  described in the "Notices" section.  This is a public OpenID Foundation
  document and not a private document, as the private="..." declaration could
  be taken to indicate.
-->
<rfc category="std" docName="openid-connect-federation-1_0" ipr="none">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="5" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="OpenID Connect Federation">OpenID Connect Federation 1.0 -
      draft 11
    </title>

    <author fullname="Roland Hedberg" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Hedberg">
      <organization>independent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>roland@catalogix.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>

      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>

        <uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andreas &Aring;kre Solberg" initials="A.&Aring;."
            surname="Solberg">
      <organization abbrev="Uninett">Uninett AS</organization>

      <address>
        <email>andreas.solberg@uninett.no</email>

        <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreassolberg/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Samuel Gulliksson" initials="S." surname="Gulliksson">
      <organization abbrev="Schibsted">Schibsted Media Group</organization>

      <address>
        <email>samuel.gulliksson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization abbrev="Yubico">Yubico</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.thread-safe.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="21" month="January" year="2020"/>

    <workgroup>OpenID Connect Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>OpenID</keyword>
    <keyword>Connect</keyword>
    <keyword>Federation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The OpenID Connect standard specifies how a Relying Party (RP)
        can discover metadata about an OpenID Provider (OP), and then
        register to obtain RP credentials. The discovery and
        registration process does not involve any mechanisms of
        dynamically establishing trust in the exchanged information, but
        instead rely on out-of-band trust establishment.
      </t>
      <t>
        In an identity federation context, this is not sufficient. The
        participants of the federation must be able to trust information
        provided about other participants in the federation. OpenID
        Connect Federations specifies how trust can be dynamically
        obtained by resolving trust from a common trusted third party.
      </t>
      <t>
        While this specification is primarily targeting OpenID Connect,
        it is designed to allow for re-use by other
        protocols and in other use cases.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        This specification describes how two entities that would like to
        interact can dynamically fetch and resolve trust and metadata for a
        given protocol through the use of third-party trust anchor. A trust
        anchor is an entity whose main purpose is to issue statements
        about entities, such as OpenID Connect Relying Parties, OpenID
        Providers, and participating organizations.
        An identity federation can be realized using this specification using
        one or more levels of trust issuers. This specification does not mandate
        a specific way or restrict how a federation may be built. Instead, the
        specification provides the basic technical trust infrastructure building
        blocks needed to build a dynamic and distributed trust network such as a
        federation.
      </t>
      <t>
        Note that this specification only concerns itself with how two entities
        in a federation gets to know about each other it does not change
        any other functionality in OpenID Connect.
      </t>
      <t>
        Note that a company, as with any real-world organization, may be
        represented by more than one entity in a federation.
      </t>
      <t>
        OpenID Connect Federation trust chains rely on
        cryptographically signed
	<xref target="RFC7519">JSON Web Token (JWT)</xref> documents,
	and the trust chain does not at
        all rely on TLS
        <xref target="RFC8446"/>
        in order to establish trust.
      </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>
          This specification uses the terms
          "Claim Name", "Claim Value", "JSON Web Token (JWT)",
          defined by
          <xref target="RFC7519">JSON Web Token (JWT)</xref>
          and the terms "OpenID Provider (OP)" and "Relying Party (RP)" defined
          by <xref target="OpenID.Core">OpenID Connect Core 1.0</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          This specification also defines the following terms:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Entity">
              <vspace/>
              Something that has a separate and distinct existence and that can
              be identified in a context. All entities in an OpenID Connect
              federation MUST have a globally unique identifier.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Entity statement">
              <vspace/>
              An entity statement is
              issued by an entity, which pertains to a subject entity and leaf
              entities. An entity statement is always a signed JWT.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Intermediate entity">
              <vspace/>
              An entity that issues
              an entity statement that appears somewhere in between those
              issued by the trust anchor and the leaf entity in a trust chain.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Leaf Entity">
              <vspace/>
              An entity defined by a certain protocol,
              e.g., OpenID Connect Relying Party or Provider.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Trust Anchor">
              <vspace/>
              An entity that represents a trusted third party.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Trust Chain">
              <vspace/>
              A sequence of entity statements that represents a chain
              starting at a leaf entity and ending in a trust anchor.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Components" anchor="components">
      <section anchor="entity-statement" title="Entity Statement ">
        <t>
          An entity statement is
          issued by an entity and concerns a subject entity and leaf entities
          in a federation. An entity statement is always a signed JWT.
          All entities in a federation SHOULD be prepared to publish an entity
          statement about themselves. If they are not able to do so themselves
          someone else MUST do it for them.
        </t>
        <t>
          An entity statement is composed of the following claims:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="iss">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the issuer of
              the statement. If the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> and
              the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> are identical, the
              issuer is making a statement about itself.
            </t>
            <t hangText="sub">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the subject
            </t>
            <t hangText="iat">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. The time the statement was issued.
              Its value is a JSON number representing the number of seconds from
              1970-01-01T0:0:0Z as measured in UTC until the date/time.
              See <xref target="RFC3339">RFC 3339</xref> for
              details regarding date/times in general and UTC in particular.
            </t>
            <t hangText="exp">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED.
              Expiration time on or after which the statement MUST NOT be
              accepted for processing. Its value is a JSON number representing
              the number of seconds from 1970-01-01T0:0:0Z as measured in UTC
              until the date/time.
            </t>
            <t hangText="jwks">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. A
              <xref target="RFC7517">JSON Web Key Set (JWKS)</xref>
              representing the public part of the subject
              entity's signing keys. The corresponding private key is
              used by leaf entities to sign entity statements about themselves,
              and intermediate entities to sign statements about other entities.
              The keys that can be found here are primarily intended to sign
              entity statements and should not be used in other protocols.
            </t>
            <t hangText="aud">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL.
              The entity statement may be specifically created for an entity.
              The entity identifier for that entity MUST appear in this claim.
            </t>
            <t hangText="authority_hints">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. Array of strings representing
              the entity identifiers of intermediate entities or trust anchors
              that may issue an entity statement about the issuer entity.
              For all entities except for trust anchors that do not have any
              superiors this is REQUIRED and MUST NOT be the empty list [].
              This claim MUST be absent in an
              entity statement issued by a trust anchor with no superiors.
            </t>
            <t hangText="metadata">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. JSON object including protocol
              specific metadata claims that represent the entity's metadata.
              Each key of the JSON object represents a metadata type
              identifier, and each value MUST be a JSON object representing
              the metadata according to the metadata schema of that metadata
              type. An entity statement may contain multiple
              metadata statements, but only one for each metadata type.
              If the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> of an entity statement
              points to the same entity as the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>
              then the entity statement MUST contain a
              <spanx style="verb">metadata</spanx> claim.
            </t>
            <t hangText="metadata_policy">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. JSON object that describes
              a metadata policy.
              Each key of the JSON object represents a metadata type
              identifier, and each value MUST be a JSON object representing
              the metadata policy according to the metadata schema of that
              metadata type. An entity statement may contain multiple
              metadata policy statements, but only one for each metadata type.
              Only non-leaf entities MAY contain a
              <spanx style="verb">metadata_policy</spanx>
              claim. Leaf entities MUST NOT contain a metadata_policy claim.
            </t>
            <t hangText="constraints">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. JSON object that describes a set of trust chain
              constraints. More about this in <xref target="chain_constraints"/>
            </t>
            <t hangText="crit">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL.
              The <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> (critical) entity statement
              claim
              indicates that extensions to entity statement claims defined by
              this specification
              are being used that MUST be understood and processed.
              It is used in the same way that
              <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx>
              is used for extension <xref target="RFC7515">JWS</xref> header
              parameters that MUST be understood and processed.
              Its value is an array listing the entity statement claims
              present in the entity statement that use those extensions.
              If any of the listed extension entity statement claims are not
              understood and supported by the recipient, then the entity
              statement is invalid.
              Producers MUST NOT include entity statement claim names defined by
              this specification or
              names that do not occur as entity statement claim names in the
              entity statement
              in the <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> list.
              Producers MUST NOT use the empty list
              <spanx style="verb">[]</spanx>
              as the <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> value.
            </t>
            <t hangText="policy_language_crit">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL.
              The <spanx style="verb">policy_language_crit</spanx> (critical)
              entity statement claim
              indicates that extensions to the policy language defined by this
              specification
              are being used that MUST be understood and processed.
              It is used in the same way that
              <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx>
              is used for extension
	      <xref target="RFC7515">JSON Web Signature (JWS)</xref>
	      header parameters that MUST be
              understood and processed.
              Its value is an array listing the policy language extensions
              present in the policy language statements that use those
              extensions.
              If any of the listed extension policy language extensions are not
              understood and supported by the recipient, then the entity
              statement is invalid.
              Producers MUST NOT include policy language names defined by this
              specification or
              names that do not occur in policy language statements in the
              entity statement
              in the <spanx style="verb">policy_language_crit</spanx> list.
              Producers MUST NOT use the empty list
              <spanx style="verb">[]</spanx>
              as the <spanx style="verb">policy_language_crit</spanx> value.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The entity statement is signed using the private key of the issuer
          entity, in the form of a <xref target="RFC7515">JSON Web Signature
          (JWS)</xref>.
        </t>

        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The following is a non-normative example of an entity statement
            before
            serialization and adding a signature. The example contains
            a critical extension <spanx style="verb">jti</spanx> (JWT ID) to the
            entity statement and one critical extension to the policy language
            <spanx style="verb">regexp</spanx>
            (Regular expression).
          </preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "iss": "https://feide.no",
  "sub": "https://ntnu.no",
  "iat": 1516239022,
  "exp": 1516298022,
  "crit": ["jti"],
  "jti": "7l2lncFdY6SlhNia",
  "policy_language_crit": ["regexp"],
  "metadata_policy": {
    "openid_provider": {
      "issuer": {"value": "https://ntnu.no"},
      "organization_name": {"value": "NTNU"},
      "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported":
        {"subset_of": ["RS256", "RS384", "RS512"]},
      "op_policy_uri": {
        "regexp": "^https:\/\/[\w-]+\.example\.com\/[\w-]+\.html"}
    },
    "openid_relying_party": {
      "organization_name": {"value": "NTNU"},
      "grant_types_supported": {
        "subset_of": ["authorization_code", "implicit"]},
      "scopes": {
        "subset_of": ["openid", "profile", "email", "phone"]}
    }
  },
  "constraints": {
    "max_path_length": 2
  }
  "jwks": {
    "keys": [
      {
        "alg": "RS256",
        "e": "AQAB",
        "ext": true,
        "key_ops": ["verify"],
        "kid": "key1",
        "kty": "RSA",
        "n": "pnXBOusEANuug6ewezb9J_...",
        "use": "sig"
      }
    ]
  },
  "authority_hints": [
    "https://edugain.org/federation"
  ]
}
]]></artwork>

        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Trust Chain" anchor="trust_chain">
        <t>
          In an OpenID Connect Identity Federation, entities that together build
          a trust chain can be categorized as:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Trust anchor">
              <vspace/>
              An entity that represents a trusted
              third party
            </t>
            <t hangText="Leaf">
              <vspace/>
              In an OpenID Connect Identity Federation, an RP or an OP
            </t>
            <t hangText="Intermediate">
              <vspace/>
              Neither a leaf nor a trust anchor
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          A trust chain begins with a leaf entity's self-signed entity
          statement, has zero or more entity statements
          issued by intermediates about subordinates, and ends with an
          entity statement issued by the trust anchor about the top-most
          intermediate (if there are intermediates) or the leaf entity
          (if there are no intermediates).
        </t>
        <t>
          A simple example: If we have an RP that belongs to organization A
          that is a member of federation F, the trust chain for such a setup
          will contain the following entity statements:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              A self-signed entity statement about the RP published by the RP
            </t>
            <t>
              An entity statement about the RP published by Organization A
            </t>
            <t>
              An entity statement about Organization A published by Federation
              F
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          A trust chain MUST always be possible to order such that:
          If we name the entity statements ES[0] (the leaf entity's
          self-signed entity statement) to ES[i] (an entity statement issued
          by the trust anchor), i>0 then:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              The <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> entity in one entity statement
              is always the
              <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>
              entity in the next.
              ES[j]['iss'] == ES[j+1]['sub'], j=0,...,i-1
            </t>
            <t>
              There MUST always be a signing key carried in the
              <spanx style="verb">jwks</spanx>
              claim in
              ES[j] that can be used to verify the signature of ES[j-1],
              j=i,...,1 .
            </t>
            <t>
              It MUST be possible to verify the signature of ES[0] with
              one of the keys in ES[0]['jwks'].
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The signing key that MUST be used to verify ES[i] is distributed
          from the trust anchors to the any entity that needs to verify a
          trust chain in some secure out-of-band way not described in this
          document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="metadata" title="Metadata">
      <t>
        This specification does allow new metadata
        types to be defined, to support use cases outside OpenID Connect
        federations.
        The metadata type identifier will uniquely identify which metadata
        specification to utilize.
      </t>
      <t>
        The metadata document MUST be a JSON document. Beyond that there is
        no restriction.
      </t>
      <t>
        Metadata used in federations typically re-uses existing metadata
        standards.
        If needed, the metadata schema is extended
        with additional properties relevant in a federated context.
        For instance, for OpenID Connect Federations, this specification uses
        metadata values from
	<xref target="OpenID.Discovery">OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</xref> and
	<xref target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</xref>
	and adds additional
        values used for federations.
      </t>

      <section title="RP Metadata" anchor="RP_metadata">
        <t>
          The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid_relying_party</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All parameters defined in Section 2 of
          <xref target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</xref>
          are allowed in a metadata statement.
        </t>
        <t>
          To that list is added:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="federation_type">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. Array of strings specifying the federation types
              supported. Values defined by this specification are
              <spanx style="verb">automatic</spanx>
              and
              <spanx style="verb">explicit</spanx>.
            </t>
            <t hangText="organization_name">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. A human readable
              name representing the organization owning the RP.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="OP Metadata" anchor="OP_metadata">
        <t>
          The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">openid_provider</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All parameters defined in Section 3 of
          <xref target="OpenID.Discovery">OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</xref>
          are applicable.
        </t>
        <t>
          In addition, the following parameters are defined by this
          specification:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="federation_types_supported">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. Array specifying the federation types supported.
              Federation type values defined by this specification are
              <spanx style="verb">automatic</spanx>
              and <spanx style="verb">explicit</spanx>.
            </t>
            <t hangText="organization_name">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. A human readable
              name representing the organization owning the OP. It is
              intended to be used in the user interface, being recognized by
              the end users that would be using the OP to authenticate.
            </t>
            <t hangText="federation_registration_endpoint">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL.
              URL of the OP's Federation specific Dynamic Client Registration
              Endpoint. If the OP supports explicit client
              registration as described in <xref target="explicit"/>,
              then this claim is REQUIRED.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="OAuth Authorization Server">
        <t>
          The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">oauth_authorization_server</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All parameters defined in Section 2 of
          <xref target="RFC8414">RFC 8414</xref>
          are applicable.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="OAuth Client">
        <t>
          The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">oauth_client</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All parameters defined in Section 2 of
          <xref target="RFC7591">RFC 7591</xref>
          are applicable.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="OAuth Protected Resource">
        <t>
          The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">oauth_resource</spanx>.
          There is no standard that specifies what parameters that can occur
          in the metadata for this kind of entity. So for the time being, this
          can be regarded as a place holder.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Federation Entity">
        <t>
          The metadata type identifier is
          <spanx style="verb">federation_entity</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          All entities participating in a federation are of this type.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following properties are allowed:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="federation_api_endpoint">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL.
              The endpoint used for the Federation API described in
              <xref target="federation_api"/>. Intermediate entities and
              trust anchors MUST publish a federation_api_endpoint.
              Leaf entities MUST NOT.
            </t>
            <t hangText="trust_anchor_id">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL.
              An OP MUST use this claim to tell the RP which trust anchor it
              chose to use when responding to an explicit client registration.
              The value of trust_anchor_id is the entity identifier of a trust
              anchor.
            </t>
            <t hangText="name">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. String. The human readable name
              describing the subject entity. This may be, for example, the
              name of an organization.
            </t>
            <t hangText="contacts">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. JSON array with one or more
              strings. Contact persons at the entity.
              These may contain names, e-mail addresses, descriptions, phone
              numbers, etc.
            </t>
            <t hangText="policy_uri">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. URL to documentation of
              conditions and policies relevant to this entity.
            </t>
            <t hangText="homepage_uri">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. URL to a generic home page
              representing this entity.
            </t>
            <t hangText="trust_marks">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. A JSON array of signed JSON Web Token each representing
              a certification mark. More about certification marks in
              <xref target="trust_marks"/>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Example</t>
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"federation_entity": {
    "federation_api_endpoint":
        "https://example.com/federation_api_endpoint",
    "name": "The example cooperation",
    "homepage_uri": "https://www.example.com"
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Federation Policy" anchor="federation_policy">
    <section title="Applying Policy to Metadata">
      <t>
        The metadata for a specific entity can be constructed by
        combining the metadata polices defined by the trust anchor and possible
        intermediates starting with the trust anchor and the applying this
        combined policy to the metadata information in a leaf entity's entity
        statement.
      </t>

      <section title="Policy Language" anchor="PolicyLanguage">
        <t>
          Policies are expressed using a JSON object.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following keywords represent different
          actions/checks that MUST be applied to the metadata.
        </t>

        <section title="subset_of" anchor="subset_of">
          <t>
            The resulting value of the claim will be the intersection of the
            values specified here and the values of the claim. For
            instance, the claim policy:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "response_types": {
    "subset_of": ["code", "code token", "code id_token"]}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            if applied to a metadata statement with:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "response_types": ["code", "code id_token token", "code id_token"]
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            will update the claim in the metadata statement to be:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "response_types": ["code", "code id_token"]
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="one_of" anchor="one_of">
          <t>
            The value of the claim MUST be one of the ones listed here.
            As an example, if the claim policy:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "request_object_signing_alg": {
    "one_of": ["ES256", "ES384", "ES512"]}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            is applied to the metadata statement
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "request_object_signing_alg": "ES384"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            the resulting claim statement will be:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "request_object_signing_alg": "ES384"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            If an entity tries to register a value that is not in the
            <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx>
            set of values,
            applying the policy MUST lead to a failure.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="superset_of" anchor="superset_of">
          <t>The values of the claim MUST contain the ones listed here.
            We define superset the mathematical way, that is equality is
            included.
            As an example, if the claim policy:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
 "request_object_signing_alg_values_supported": {
    "superset": ["ES256", "RS256"]}
                ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>is applied to the metadata statement</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"request_object_signing_alg_values_supported": [
  "ES256", "ES384", "RS256", "RS512"]
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>the resulting claim statement will be:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"request_object_signing_alg_values_supported": [
  "ES256", "ES384", "RS256", "RS512"]
 ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            If an entity tries to register a set of values that are not
            a superset of the ones specified by
            <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>,
            applying the policy MUST lead to a failure.
          </t>

        </section>
        <section title="add" anchor="add">
          <t>
            Adds the value or values specified to the list of values for the
            metadata statement claim.
            If the specified value is already present in the list,
            this operation has no effect.
            If the claim has no value then the claim is initialized with the
            specified value.
            As an example, if the claim policy:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "contacts": {
    "add": "support@federation.example.com"}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            is applied to the following claim in the metadata statement:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "contacts": "support@org.example.com"
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            the end result will be the claim:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "contacts": ["support@org.example.com",
               "support@federation.example.com"]
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="value" anchor="value">
          <t>
            Disregarding what value the claim had,
            if any, the claims value will be set to what is specified here.
            As an example, if the claim policy:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": {
    "value": true}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            is applied to a metadata statement with the claim
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": false
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            then the metadata statement will afterwards contain:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": true
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="default" anchor="default">
          <t>
            If no value is assigned to this claim, then the claim's value
            will be set to what is specified here.
            As an example, if the claim policy:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": {
    "default": true }
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            is applied to a metadata statement with the claim
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": false
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            then the metadata statement will afterwards contain:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": false
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            If on the other hand, the metadata statement did not contain a
            <spanx style="verb">require_auth_time</spanx>
            claim then the
            following claim statement would be added to the metadata
            statement:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "require_auth_time": true
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="essential" anchor="essential">
          <t>
            If 'true' then claim MUST have a value.
            <spanx style="verb">essential</spanx>
            can be
            combined with all the other types.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  "tos_uri": {
    "essential": true}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The upshot of applying this policy to a metadata statement
            is that the metadata statement MUST contain such a claim
            otherwise the metadata statement is incorrect.
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>
      <section title="Policy Type Combinations" anchor="policy_type_combo">
        <t>
          An entity may use more then one policy type when expressing a policy
          for a claim. These are the policy types that can be combined in a
          metadata_policy statement:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="essential">
              <vspace/>
              Can be combined with all the others. If
              <spanx style="verb">essential</spanx>
              is not present that is the same as stating essential=true.
            </t>
            <t hangText="default">
              <vspace/>
              Can be combined with <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx>,
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>
              and <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>.
              If a <spanx style="verb">default</spanx> policy is combined
              with <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx>,
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>
              or
              <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>
              and it is not a
              subset of the <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx> policy or the
              <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx>
              policy or a superset of the
              <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>
              policy then an error MUST be raised.
            </t>
            <t hangText="superset_of">
              <vspace/>
              Can be combined with <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>.
              If <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx> and
              <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>
              both appears in a
              metadata_policy statement
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>
              MUST be a superset of <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>.
            </t>
            <t hangText="subset_of">
              <vspace/>
              Can be combined with <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>.
              If <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx> and
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>
              both appears in a metadata_policy statement for a claim
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>
              MUST be a superset of <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>.
            </t>
            <t hangText="value">
              <vspace/>
              Can be combined with <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx>,
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>
              and <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>.
              Here the order matters. If <spanx style="verb">value</spanx>
              appear in a superiors policy statement then the others MUST be
              ignored. If <spanx style="verb">value</spanx> are defined by the
              subordinate then it MUST be a subset of
              <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>, superset of
              <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx> and one of
              <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Combining Policies">
        <t>
          If there is more than one metadata policy in a trust chain, then
          the policies MUST be combined before they are applied to the
          metadata statement.
        </t>
        <t>
          Using the notation we have defined in
          <xref target="trust_chain"/>
          policies
          are combined starting with ES[i] and then adding the policies from
          ES[j] j=i-1,..,1 before applying the combined policy to the entity's
          metadata.
        </t>
        <t>
          After having combined the policies, the policy for each claim MUST
          adhere to the rules defined in <xref target="policy_type_combo"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          These are the policy types that can be combined when combining two
          policies:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="subset_of">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx> policies
              is the intersection of the values.
            </t>
            <t hangText="one_of">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx> policies
              is the intersection of the values.
            </t>
            <t hangText="superset_of">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two
              <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx>
              policies is the intersection of the values.
            </t>
            <t hangText="add">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two <spanx style="verb">add</spanx> policies
              is the union of the values.
            </t>
            <t hangText="value">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two <spanx style="verb">value</spanx> policies
              is NOT allowed unless the two values are equal.
            </t>
            <t hangText="default">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two <spanx style="verb">default</spanx> policies
              is NOT allowed unless the two values are equal.
            </t>
            <t hangText="essential">
              <vspace/>
              The result of combining two <spanx style="verb">essential</spanx> policies
              is True if any of the values are True otherwise it is False.
              Note that a missing <spanx style="verb">essential</spanx> specification
              is to be treated as an essential=true statement.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          It should be noted that applying <spanx style="verb">subset_of</spanx>,
          <spanx style="verb">superset_of</spanx> or
          <spanx style="verb">one_of</spanx> to an empty value will result in
          an empty value.
        </t>
        <section title="Policy Combination Example">
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              A federations policy for RPs:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "scopes": {
        "subset_of": ["openid", "eduperson", "phone"],
        "superset_of": ["openid"],
        "default": ["openid", "eduperson"]},
    "id_token_signed_response_alg": {
        "one_of": ["ES256", "ES384", "ES512"]},
    "contacts": {
        "add": "helpdesk@federation.example.org"},
    "application_type": {"value": "web"}
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              An organization's policy for RPs:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "scopes": {
        "subset_of": ["openid", "eduperson", "address"],
        "default": ["openid", "eduperson"]},
    "id_token_signed_response_alg": {
        "one_of": ["ES256", "ES384"],
        "default": "ES256"},
    "contacts": {
        "add": "helpdesk@org.example.org"}
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The combined metadata policy then becomes:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "scopes": {
        "subset_of": ["openid", "eduperson"],
        "superset_of": ["openid"],
        "default": ["openid", "eduperson"]},
    "id_token_signed_response_alg": {
        "one_of": ["ES256", "ES384"],
        "default": "ES256"},
    "contacts": {
        "add": ["helpdesk@federation.example.org",
                "helpdesk@org.example.org"]},
    "application_type": {
        "value": "web"}
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Enforcing Policy">
        <t>
          If applying policies to a metadata statement results in incorrect
          metadata, then such a metadata statement MUST
          be regarded as broken and MUST NOT be used.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Extending the Policy Language">
        <t>
          There might be parties that want to extend the policy language
          defined here. If that happens then the rule is that if
          software compliant with this specification
          encounters a keyword it doesn't understand it MUST ignore it
          unless it is listed in a
	  <spanx style="verb">policy_language_crit</spanx> list,
          as is done for <xref target="RFC7515">JWS</xref> header parameters
          with the <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> parameter.
          If the policy language extension keyword
          is listed in the <spanx style="verb">policy_language_crit</spanx> list
          and not understood, then the metadata MUST be rejected.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Policy Example">
        <t>
          The following is a non-normative example of a set of policies being
          applied to an RP's metadata.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The RP's metadata:
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "contacts": ["rp_admins@cs.example.com"],
  "redirect_uris": ["https://cs.example.com/rp1"],
  "response_types": ["code"]
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The federation's policy for RPs:
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "scopes": {
        "superset_of": ["openid", "eduperson"],
        "default": ["openid", "eduperson"]
    },
    "response_types": {
        "subset_of": ["code", "code id_token"]}
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The organization's policy for RPs:
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "contacts": {
    "add": "helpdesk@example.com"},
  "logo_uri": {
    "one_of": ["https://example.com/logo_small.jpg",
               "https://example.com/logo_big.jpg"],
    "default": "https://example.com/logo_small.jpg"
  },
  "policy_uri": {
    "value": "https://example.com/policy.html"},
  "tos_uri": {
    "value": "https://example.com/tos.html"}
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The metadata for the entity in question after applying the policies
          above, would then become:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "contacts": ["rp_admins@cs.example.com", "helpdesk@example.com"],
  "logo_uri": "https://example.com/logo_small.jpg",
  "policy_uri": "https://example.com/policy.html",
  "tos_uri": "https://example.com/tos.html",
  "scopes": ["openid", "eduperson"],
  "response_types": ["code"],
  "redirect_uris": ["https://cs.example.com/rp1"]
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
      <section title="Applying Constraints" anchor="chain_constraints">
        <t>A constraint specification can contain the following claims:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="max_path_length">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. Integer. The maximum number of entities statements
              between this entity statement and the last entity statement in
              the trust chain.
            </t>
            <t hangText="naming_constraints">
              <vspace/>
              OPTIONAL. JSON object. Restriction on the entity identifiers of the
              entities below this entity. The behavior of this claim mimics
              what is defined in Section 4.2.1.10 in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
              Restrictions are defined in terms of permitted or excluded name
              subtrees.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>The following is a non-normative example of such a specification:</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "naming_constraints": {
    "permitted": [
      "https://.example.com"
    ],
    "excluded": [
      "https://east.example.com"
    ]
  },
  "max_path_length": 2
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          If a subordinate entity statement contains a constraint specification
          that is more restrictive then the one in effect, then the more
          restrictive constraint is in effect from here on.
        </t>
        <t>
          If a subordinate entity statement contains a constraint specification
          that is less restrictive then the one in effect, then it MUST be
          ignored.
        </t>
        <section title="Max Path Length" anchor="max_path_length">
          <t>
            The <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> constraint specifies the maximum number of
            entity statement a trust chain can have between the entity statement
            that contains the constraint specification and the leaf's entity
            statement.
          </t>
          <t>
            A <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> constraint of zero indicates that no
            entity statement may appear between this entity statement and the
            leaf entity statement. Where it appears, the <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> constraint
            MUST have a value that is greater than or equal to zero.
            Where <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> does not appear, no limit is imposed.
          </t>
          <t>
            Assuming that we have a trust chain with four entity statements:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Leaf entity (LE)</t>
              <t>Intermediate 1 (I1)</t>
              <t>Intermediate 2 (I2)</t>
              <t>Trust Anchor (TA)</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Then the trust chain fulfills the constraints if:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                The TA specifies a <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> that is equal to or bigger
                then 2.
              </t>
              <t>
                TA specifies <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> of 2, I2 specifies <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> of 1,
                and I1 specifies no <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> constraint.
              </t>
              <t>Neither TA nor I2 specifies any <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> constraint
                while I1 specifies <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> of 0.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            The trust chain does not fulfill the constraints if:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>TA has specified <spanx style="verb">max_path_length</spanx> of 1.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Naming Constraints" anchor="naming_constraints">
        <t>
          The name constraints indicates a name space within which all subject
          entity identifiers in subordinate entity statements in a trust chain
          MUST be located.
        </t>
          <t>
            Restrictions are defined in terms of permitted or excluded name
            subtrees.  Any name matching a restriction in the excluded
            claim is invalid regardless of information appearing in the
            permitted claim.
          </t>
          <t>
            The constraint MUST be specified as a fully qualified domain name
            and MAY specify a host or a domain.  Examples would be
            "host.example.com" and ".example.com".  When the constraint begins
            with a period, it MAY be expanded with one or more labels.
            That is, the constraint ".example.com" is satisfied by both
            host.example.com and my.host.example.com.  However, the constraint
            ".example.com" is not satisfied by "example.com".  When the
            constraint does not begin with a period, it specifies a host.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Trust Marks" anchor="trust_marks">
        <t>In this specification we use the US NSTIC definition</t>
        <t>"A trustmark is used to indicate that a product or service provider
          has met the requirements of the Identity Ecosystem, as determined
          by an accreditation authority"</t>
        <t>Technically trust marks as used by this specification are signed
        JWTs that represents a statement of conformance to a well-scoped
          set of trust and/or interoperability requirements.</t>
        <t>The trust marks are signed by an by the federation accredited
        authority. The validation of such a signed statement is performed
        in the same way as a self-signed entity statement is validated</t>
        <section title="Trust mark properties" anchor="trust_prop">
          <t>These are the properties that can occur in a trust mark:</t>
          <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="iss">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. String. The issuer of the trust mark.
            </t>
            <t hangText="sub">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. String. The entity this trust mark applies to.
            </t>
            <t hangText="id">
              REQUIRED. String. An identifier of the trust mark.
            </t>
            <t hangText="mark">
              REQUIRED. String. An URL that points to a mark/logo that the
              subject is allowed to display to a user of the entity.
            </t>
            <t hangText="iat">
              REQUIRED. INT. When this trust mark was issued. Expressed as
              seconds since epoch.
            </t>
            <t hangText="exp">
              OPTIONAL. INT. When this trust mark is not valid anymore.
              Expresses as seconds since epoch. If not present it means that
              the trust mark is valid forever.
            </t>
            <t hangText="ref">
              OPTIONAL. String. URL that points to information connected to
              the issuance of this trust mark.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Validating a trust mark" anchor="trust_valid">
          <t>An entity should not try to validate a trust mark until
          it knows which trust anchors it wants to use.</t>
          <t>validating a trust mark follows the procedure set out in
            <xref target="resolving_trust" />
          </t>
          <t>Note that the entity representing the accreditation authority
          MUST be immediately below the trust anchor. There can not be any
          intermediate between it and the trust anchor.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Trust mark example" anchor="trust_example">
          <figure>
            <preamble>An example of a self-signed certification mark</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "iss": "https://example.com/op",
  "sub": "https://example.com/op",
  "iat": 1579621160,
  "id": "https://openid.net/certification/op",
  "mark": "http://openid.net/wordpress-content/uploads/2016/05/
           oid-l-certification-mark-l-cmyk-150dpi-90mm.jpg",
  "ref": "https://openid.net/wordpress-content/uploads/2015/09/
           RolandHedberg-pyoidc-0.7.7-Basic-26-Sept-2015.zip"
}]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <preamble>An example of a 3rd party accreditation authority</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "iss": "https://swamid.sunet.se",
  "sub": "https://umu.se/op",
  "iat": 1577833200,
  "exp": 1609369200,
  "id": "https://refeds.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Sirtfi-1.0.pdf",
}]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section
            title="Obtaining Federation Entity Configuration Information"
            anchor="federation_configuration">
      <t>
        The configuration endpoint is found using the
	<xref target="RFC8615">Well-Known URIs</xref>
	specification, with the suffix
        <spanx style="verb">openid-federation</spanx>. The scheme, host and port
        is taken directly from the entity identifier combined with the following
        path: <spanx style="verb">/.well-known/openid-federation</spanx>.
      </t>
      <t>
        If the entity identifier contains a path, it is concatenated after
        <spanx style="verb">/.well-known/openid-federation</spanx>
        in the same
        manner
        that path components are concatenated to the well-known identifier in
        the OAuth 2.0 Authorization Server Metadata
        <xref target="RFC8414"/>
        specification.
        Of course, in real multi-tenant deployments, in which the entity identifier
        might be of the form
        <spanx style="verb">https://multi-tenant-service.example.com/my-tenant-identifier</spanx>
        the tenant is very likely to not have control over the path
        <spanx style="verb">https://multi-tenant-service.example.com/.well-known/openid-federation/my-tenant-identifier</spanx>
        whereas it is very likely to have control over the path
        <spanx style="verb">https://multi-tenant-service.example.com/my-tenant-identifier/.well-known/openid-federation</spanx>.
        Therefore, if using the configuration endpoint at the URL with the tenant path
        after the well-known part fails,
        it is RECOMMENDED that callers retry at the URL with the tenant path
        before the well-known part
        (even though this violates <xref target="RFC8615"/>).
      </t>
      <t>
        Federation Entities MUST make an Entity Configuration Document available
        at the configuration endpoint.
      </t>
      <section title="Federation Entity Configuration Request">
        <t>
          A federation Entity Configuration Document MUST be queried using an
          HTTP GET request at the previously specified path.
          The requesting party would make the following request to the Entity
          <spanx style="verb">https://example.com</spanx>
          to obtain its
          Configuration information:
        </t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[

  GET /.well-known/openid-federation HTTP/1.1
  Host: example.com
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Federation Entity Configuration Response">
        <t>The response is a self-signed Entity Statement, as described in
          <xref target="entity-statement">entity statement</xref>.
          If the entity is an intermediate entity or a trust anchor the
          response MUST contain metadata for a federation entity.
        </t>
        <t>
          A positive response is a signed entity statement, where the content
          type MUST be set to <spanx style="verb">application/jose</spanx>.
	  In case of an error, the response
          will be a JSON object, the content type MUST be set to
          <spanx style="verb">application/json</spanx> and
	  the error response uses the applicable HTTP status code value.
        </t>
        <t>The following is a non-normative example response from an
          intermediate entity, before serialization and adding a signature:
        </t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
200 OK
Last-Modified: Thu, 29 Aug 2019 08:54:26 GMT
Content-Type: application/jose

{
  "iss": "https://example.com",
  "sub": "https://example.com",
  "iat": 1516239022,
  "exp": 1516298022,
  "metadata": {
    "federation_entity": {
      "federation_api_endpoint":
        "https://example.com/federation_api_endpoint",
      "name": "The example cooperation",
      "homepage_uri": "https://www.example.com",
    }
  },
  "jwks": {
    "keys": [
      {
        "alg": "RS256",
        "e": "AQAB",
        "ext": true,
        "key_ops": ["verify"],
        "kid": "key1",
        "kty": "RSA",
        "n": "pnXBOusEANuug6ewezb9J_...",
        "use": "sig"
      }
    ]
  }
}]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="The Federation API" anchor="federation_api">
      <t>
        All entities that are expected to publish entity statements about other
        entities MUST expose a Federation API endpoint.
      </t>
      <t>
        The federation API endpoint of an entity can be found the in the
        configuration response as described in
        <xref target="federation_configuration"/>
        or by other means.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Federation API is an HTTPS API that may support multiple
        operations. Fetching entity statements is one of the operations, and the
        only one that all Federation API endpoints are REQUIRED to support.
        All the other operations are OPTIONAL. The list of defined
        operations may be extended in a future.
      </t>
      <t>
        While all operations on the federation API endpoint make use of a
        GET request, other operations may choose to use other HTTP methods. If
        the <spanx style="verb">operation</spanx>
        parameter is left out, it is treated as a
        fetch entity statements request. Unless otherwise mentioned or agreed
        upon, requests to the federation API do not need to be
        authenticated.
      </t>

      <section title="Fetching Entity Statement (REQUIRED)">
        <t>
          Fetching entity statement is used to collect entity statements
          one by one in order to gather trust chains.
        </t>
        <t>
          In order to fetch an entity statement, an entity needs to know the
          identifier of the entity to ask (the issuer), the federation API
          endpoint of that entity and the identifier of the entity that you
          want the statement to be about (the subject).
        </t>

        <section title="Fetch Entity Statements Request"
                 anchor="fetch_statement">
          <t>
            The request MUST be an HTTP request using the GET method and
            the https scheme to a resolved federation API endpoint with the
            following query string parameters:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="operation">
                <vspace/>
                OPTIONAL. If not present, MUST be treated as
                <spanx style="verb">fetch</spanx>.
              </t>
              <t hangText="iss">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the issuer
                from which you want an entity statement issued. Because of the
                normalization of the URL, multiple issuers may resolve to a
                shared federation API. This parameter makes it explicit exactly
                which issuer we want entity statements from.
              </t>
              <t hangText="sub">
                <vspace/>
                OPTIONAL. The entity identifier of the subject
                for which you would like an entity statement issued. If this
                parameter is left out, it is considered to be the same as the
                issuer and would indicate a request for a self-issued
                statement.
              </t>
              <t hangText="aud">
                <vspace/>
                OPTIONAL. The entity identifier of the
                requester. If the aud parameter is present in the request,
                the <spanx style="verb">aud</spanx> claim SHOULD be present in
                the entity statement response and take exactly that value.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The following is a non-normative example of an API
              request for an entity statement:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /federation_api_endpoint?
iss=https%3A%2F%2Fopenid.sunet.se%2Ffederation HTTP/1.1
Host: openid.sunet.se
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Fetch Entity Statements Response">
          <t>
            A positive response is a signed entity statement where
            the content type MUST be set to
            <spanx style="verb">application/jose</spanx>.
            If it is negative response it will be a JSON object and the
            content type MUST be set to
            <spanx style="verb">application/json</spanx>.
            See more about error responses in <xref target="error_response"/>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The following is a non-normative example of a response, before
              serialization and adding a signature:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
200 OK
Last-Modified: Mon, 17 Dec 2018 11:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/jose

{
  "iss": "https://openid.sunet.se",
  "sub": "https://openid.sunet.se",
  "iat": 1516239022,
  "exp": 1516298022,
  "metadata": {
    "openid_relying_party": {
      "application_type": "web",
      "redirect_uris": [ "https://openid.sunet.se/rp/callback" ],
      "organization_name": "SUNET",
      "logo_uri": "https://www.sunet.se/sunet/images/32x32.png",
      "grant_types": ["authorization_code", "implicit"],
      "jwks_uri": "https://openid.sunet.se/rp/jwks.json"
    }
  },
  "jwks": {
    "keys": [
      {
        "alg": "RS256",
        "e": "AQAB",
        "ext": true,
        "key_ops": ["verify"],
        "kid": "key1",
        "kty": "RSA",
        "n": "pnXBOusEANuug6ewezb9J_...",
        "use": "sig"
      }
    ]
  },
  "authority_hints": [
      "https://edugain.org/federation"
  ]
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Trust Negotiation (OPTIONAL)">
        <t>
          An entity may use the trust negotiation operation in order to fetch
          resolved metadata about itself as seen/trusted by a remote peer.
          The result may, for instance, tell an RP what operations, scopes and
          claims an OP would allow the RP to use if a specific trust anchor
          was used.
        </t>

        <section title="Trust Negotiation Request">
          <t>
            The request MUST be an HTTP request using the GET method and
            the https scheme to a resolved federation API endpoint with the
            following query string parameters:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="operation">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. MUST be set to
		<spanx style="verb">resolve_metadata</spanx>.
              </t>
              <t hangText="respondent">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the
                entity whose metadata are requested. Because of the
                normalization of the URL, multiple entity identifiers may
                resolve to a shared federation API. This parameter makes it
                explicit exactly which entity is expected.
              </t>
              <t hangText="peer">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the entity
                the information is requested for. This must be a leaf entity.
              </t>
              <t hangText="type">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. The metadata type to resolve.
                In this document, we use the metadata types listed in
                <xref target="metadata"/>.
              </t>
              <t hangText="anchor">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. The trust anchor the remote peer
                MUST use when resolving the metadata. The value is an entity
                identifier.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The following is a non-normative example of an API
              request for trust negotiation:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /federation_api_endpoint?
operation=resolve_metadata&
respondent=https%3A%2F%2Fopenid.sunet.se%2Ffederation&
type=openid_provider&
anchor=https%3A%2F%2Fswamid.se&
peer=https%3A%2F%2Fidp.umu.se%2Fopenid HTTP/1.1
Host: openid.sunet.se
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Trust Negotiation Response">
          <t>
            The response is a metadata statement that is the result of
            applying the metadata policies in the trust chain on the entity's
            metadata.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The following is a non-normative example of a response:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
200 OK
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "organization": "University of Ume?",
  "contacts": ["legal@umu.se", "technical@umu.se"],
  "logo_uri":
    "https://www.umu.se/SRWStatic/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
  "policy_uri":
    "https://www.umu.se/en/about-the-website/legal-information/",
  "authorization_endpoint":
    "https://idp.umu.se/openid/authorization",
  "token_endpoint": "https://idp.umu.se/openid/token",
  "response_types_supported": ["code", "code id_token", "token"],
  "grant_types_supported": [
    "authorization_code",
    "implicit",
    "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
  ],
  "subject_types_supported": ["pairwise"],
  "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": ["RS256"]
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Entity Listings (OPTIONAL)">
        <t>
          An entity may query another entity for a list of all the
          entities immediately subordinate to that entity and about which
          that entity is prepared to issue statements about.
          (In some cases, this may be a very large list.)
        </t>

        <section title="Entity Listings Request">
          <t>
            The request MUST be an HTTP request using the GET method and
            the https scheme to a resolved federation API endpoint with the
            following query string parameters:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="operation">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. MUST be set to
                <spanx style="verb">listing</spanx>.
              </t>
              <t hangText="iss">
                <vspace/>
                REQUIRED. The entity identifier of the entity
                from which an entity listing is requested. Because of the
                normalization of the URL, multiple entity identifiers may
                resolve to a shared federation API. This parameter makes it
                explicit exactly which entity is expected.
              </t>
              <t hangText="is_leaf">
                <vspace/>
                OPTIONAL. If left out, result should
                include both leaf entities and intermediate nodes. If set to
                <spanx style="verb">true</spanx>,
                the response should contain only leaf entities. If set to
                <spanx style="verb">false</spanx>, the
                response should contain only intermediate nodes.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The following is a non-normative example of an API
              request for trust negotiation:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /federation_api_endpoint?
operation=listing&
iss=https%3A%2F%2Fopenid.sunet.se%2Ffederation HTTP/1.1
Host: openid.sunet.se
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Entity Listing Response">
          <t>
            The response MUST contain an JSON list with the known entity
            identifiers.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              The following is a non-normative example of a response:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
200 OK
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

[
  "https://ntnu.andreas.labs.uninett.no/",
  "https://blackboard.ntnu.no/openid/callback",
  "https://serviceprovider.andreas.labs.uninett.no/application17"
]
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Generic Error Response" anchor="error_response">
        <t>
          If the request was malformed, or some error occurred during
          processing of the request, the following standardized error format
          should be used regardless of the operation specified.
        </t>
        <t>
          The HTTP response code MUST be something in 400/500-range, giving an
          indication of the type of error. The response body MUST be a JSON
          object containing the claims below and the content type MUST
          be set to <spanx style="verb">application/json</spanx>.
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="operation">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. The operation of the request.
            </t>
            <t hangText="error">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. The error code.
            </t>
            <t hangText="error_description">
              <vspace/>
              REQUIRED. A human readable short
              text describing the error.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <figure>
          <preamble>
            The following is a non-normative example of an error response:
          </preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
400 Bad request
Last-Modified: Wed, 22 Jul 2018 19:15:56 GMT
Content-Type: application/json

{
  "operation": "fetch",
  "error": "invalid_request",
  "error_description":
    "Required request parameter [iss] was missing."
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="resolving_trust"
             title="Resolving Trust Chain and Metadata">
      <t>
        An entity (e.g., the Consumer) that wants to establish trust with a
        remote peer, must have the remote peer's entity identifier and a list of
        entity identifiers of trust anchors together with the public version
        of their signing keys. The Consumer will first have to fetch
        sufficient entity statements to establish at least one chain of trust
        from the remote peer to one or more of the configured trust anchors.
        After that the entity MUST validate the trust chains independently,
        and -- if there are multiple valid trust chains and if the
        application demands it -- choose one.
      </t>

      <section anchor="fetching-es"
               title="Fetching Entity Statements to Establish a Trust Chain">
        <t>
          Depending on the circumstances, the Consumer may either be
          handed the remote peer's self-issued entity statement, or it may
          have to fetch it by itself. If it needs to fetch it, it will use the
          process described in
          <xref target="fetch_statement"/>
          with both <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> and
          <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>
          set to the entity identifier
          of the remote peer.
        </t>
        <t>
          The next step is to iterate through the list of
          intermediates listed in
          <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx>, ignoring the authority
          hints that end in an unknown trust anchor, requesting an entity
          statement about the remote peer from each of the intermediates.
          If the received entity statement contains an authority hint this
          process is repeated. This time with the
          <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx>
          set to the
          intermediates entity identifier and the <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx> to be
          the <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> of the previous query.
          The Consumer SHOULD NOT attempt to fetch
          entity statements it already has fetched during this
          process (loop prevention).
        </t>
        <t>
          A successful operation will return one or more lists of
          entity statements. Each of the lists terminating in a self-signed
          entity statement issued by a trust anchor.
        </t>
        <t>
          If there is no path from the remote peer to at least one of the
          trusted trust anchors, then the list will be empty and there is no
          way of establishing trust in the remote peer's information. How the
          Consumer deals with this is out of scope for this specification.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Validating the Trust Chains"
               anchor="trust_chain_validation">
        <t>
          As described in <xref target="trust_chain"/>,
          a trust chain consists of an ordered list of entity
          statements. So whichever way the Consumer has acquired the set of
          entity statements, it must now verify that it is a proper trust chain
          using the rules laid out in that section.
        </t>
        <t>
          To validate the chain, the following must be done:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              For each entity statement ES[j] j=i,..,0:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>
                  Verify that the statement contains all the required claims.
                </t>
                <t>
                  Verify that <spanx style="verb">iat</spanx> has a value in the
                  past
                </t>
                <t>
                  Verify that <spanx style="verb">exp</spanx> has a value that
                  is in the future.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>
              For j=0 verify that <spanx style="verb">iss</spanx> ==
              <spanx style="verb">sub</spanx>.
            </t>
            <t>
              For j=0,...,i-1: Verify that ES[j]['iss'] == ES[j+1]['sub']
            </t>
            <t>
              For j=0,...,i-1: Verify the signature of ES[j] using the public
              key carried in ES[j+1]['jwks'].
            </t>
            <t>
              For j == 0 verify the signature of ES[0] using the public
              key carried in ES[0]['jwks'].
            </t>
            <t>
              For j == i: verify that a) the issuer matches the configured
              identifier of a trust anchor and b) its signature is valid with
              the likewise configured public key of said trust anchor.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Verifying the signature is a much more expensive
          operation then verifying the correctness of the statement and the
          timestamps. An implementer MAY therefor chose to not verify the
          signature until all the other checks have been done.
        </t>
        <t>Consumers MAY cache Entity Statements or signature verification
          results for a given time until they expire
          <xref target="trust_lifetime"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Choosing One of the Valid Trust Chains">
        <t>
          If multiple valid trust chains are found, the Consumer will
          need to decide on which one to use.
        </t>
        <t>
          One simple rule would be to prefer a shorter chain over a longer one.
        </t>
        <t>Consumers MAY follow other rules according to local policy.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trust_lifetime"
               title="Calculating the Expiration Time of a Trust Chain">
        <t>
          Each entity statement in a trust chain is signed and MUST have an
          expiration time (exp) set. The expiration time of the whole trust
          chain is set to the minimum value of exp within the chain.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Updating Metadata, Key Rollover, and Revocation">
      <t>
        This specification allows for a smooth process of updating metadata
        and public keys.
      </t>
      <t>
        As described above in <xref target="trust_lifetime"/>,
        each trust chain has an expiration time.
        A consumer of metadata using this specification MUST support
        refreshing a trust chain when it expires.
        How often a consumer should re-evaluate the trust chain depends on
        how quickly the consumer wants to find out that something has changed
        in the trust chain.
      </t>

      <section title="Protocol Key Rollover">
        <t>
          If a leaf entity publishes its public keys in the metadata part
          using <spanx style="verb">jwks</spanx>, setting an expiration time on
          the self-signed entity
          statement can be used to control how often the receiving entity is
          fetching an updated version of the public key.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Key Rollover for a Trust Anchor"
               anchor="key_rollover_anchor">
        <t>
          A trust anchor must publish a self-signed entity statement about
          itself. The trust anchor SHOULD set a reasonable expiration
          time on that statement, such that the consumers will re-fetch the
          entity statement at reasonable intervals. If the trust anchor wants to
          roll over its signing keys it would have to:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Add the new keys to the <spanx style="verb">jwks</spanx> representing
              the trust
              anchors signing keys.
            </t>
            <t>
              Keep signing the entity statement using
              the old keys for a long enough time period to allow all
              subordinates to have gotten access to the new keys.
            </t>
            <t>
              Switch to signing with the new keys.
            </t>
            <t>
              After a reasonable time period remove the old keys. What is
              regarded as a reasonable time is dependent on the security profile
              and risk assessment of the trust anchor.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          It must be taken into consideration that clients may have
          manually configured pubic keys as part of their configuration.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Revocation">
        <t>
          Since the consumers are expected to check the trust chain at regular,
          reasonably frequent times, this specification does not specify a
          standard revocation process. Specific federations may make a
          different choice and will then have to add such a process.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="OpenID Connect Communication" anchor="client_registration">
      <t>
        This section describes how the trust framework in this specification
        is used to establish trust between an RP and an OP
        that have no explicit configuration or registration in advance.
      </t>
      <t>
        There are two alternative approaches to establish trust between an
        RP and an OP, which we call automatic and explicit
        registration. Members of a federation or a community
        should agree upon which one to use. While implementations should
        support both methods, deployments may choose to disable the use of one
        of them.
      </t>
      <t>
        Independent of whether the RP uses automatic or explicit registration,
        the way that the RP learns about the OP is the same.
	It will use the procedure that is
        described in <xref target="resolving_trust"/>.
      </t>

      <section title="Automatic Registration" anchor="automatic">
        <t>
          The <spanx style="verb">client_id</spanx> of the RP
          MUST be set identically to the RP entity identifier.
        </t>
        <t>
          Without a registration process, the RP does not have a
          client_secret. Instead the automatic registration model requires the
          RP to make use of asymmetric cryptography.
        </t>
        <t>
          The RP MUST host a Federation API that allows the OP to fetch the
          entity statements.
        </t>

        <section title="The Authentication Request">
          <t>
            The authentication request is as specified in OpenID Connect
            Core.
          </t>
          <t>
            The RP MUST authenticate at the authentication endpoint
            using the private_key_jwt method described in the client
            authentication section of
            <xref target="OpenID.Core">OpenID Connect Core 1.0</xref>.
            The private_key_jwt JWT used here diverge from what is described in
            that section on a couple of points:
            <list>
              <t>The Audience (aud) SHOULD be the URL of the Authorization
                Server's Authorization Endpoint. NOT the Token Endpoint.</t>
              <t>The claim iss MUST contain the entity ID of the OAuth client</t>
              <t>The claim sub MUST contain the entity ID of the OAuth client</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>
              An authentication request example:
            </preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /authorization?
  redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fexample.com%2Fauthz_cb
  &scope=openid+profile+email+address+phone
  &response_type=code
  &nonce=4LX0mFMxdBjkGmtx7a8WIOnB&
  &state=YmX8PM9I7WbNoMnnieKKBiptVW0sP2OZ
  &client_id=https%3A%2F%2Fexample.com%3A8090%2Firp
  &client_assertion=eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIs ... qx7xHcvPOdIhnpg
  &client_assertion_type=
    urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth%3Aclient-assertion-type%3Ajwt-bearer
  HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Processing the Authentication Request">
          <t>
            When the OP receives an incoming authentication request,
            the OP supports OpenID Connect Federation, the incoming client_id
            is a valid URL and the OP does not have the client_id
            registered as a known
            client then the OP should try to resolve and fetch trust
            chains starting with the RP's entity
            statement as described in <xref target="fetching-es"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The OP should validate the possible trust chains, as described in
            <xref target="trust_chain_validation"/>,
            and resolve the RP metadata with type
            <spanx style="verb">openid_relying_party</spanx>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The OP should consider the resolved metadata of the RP, and
            verify that it complies with the client metadata specification in
            <xref target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client
              Registration 1.0</xref>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Once the OP has the RP's metadata, it can verify the client
            authentication.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Authentication Error Response">
          <t>
            If the OP fails to establish trust with the RP, it should use an
            appropriate error code, and an
            <spanx style="verb">error_description</spanx>
            that aids the RP to understand what is wrong.
          </t>
          <t>
            In addition to the error codes defined in Section 3.1.2.6 of OpenID
            Connect
            core, this specification also defines the following error codes:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="missing_trust_anchor">
                <vspace/>
                No trusted trust anchor could be found.
              </t>
              <t hangText="validation_failed">
                <vspace/>
                Trust chain validation failed.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <preamble>
                The following is a non-normative example error response:
              </preamble>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 302 Found
  Location: https://client.example.org/cb?
    error=missing_trust_anchor
    &error_description=
      Could%20not%20find%20a%20trusted%20anchor
    &state=af0ifjsldkj
]]></artwork>
            </figure>

          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Explicit Registration" anchor="explicit">
        <t>
          This method involves performing an explicit registration of a new
          client the first time an RP interacts with an OP
          using something that basically follows the steps in
          <xref target="OpenID.Registration">OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</xref>
          but where the client registration request
          is a signed entity statement.
        </t>

        <section title="Provider Discovery">
          <t>
            The RP will start by gathering the OP's metadata using the
            process specified in
            <xref target="resolving_trust"/>
            above.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Clireg" title="Client Registration">
          <section anchor="Cliregreq" title="Client Registration Request">
            <t>
              The OP MUST support OpenID Dynamic Client Registration as extended
              by this specification.
              This is signaled by having the claim
              <spanx style="verb">federation_registration_endpoint</spanx>
              in the OP's metadata.
            </t>
            <t>
              Given that the OP supports explicit registration, the RP
              progresses as follows:
            </t>
            <t>
              <list style="numbers">
                <t>
                  Once it has the list of acceptable trust chains for the OP
                  it MUST choose the subset it wants to progress with. The
                  subset can be as small as one trust chain, but it can also
                  contain more than one.
                </t>
                <t>
                  Based on the trust anchors referenced in the subset of
                  trust chains, the RP will choose a set of
                  <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx>
                  from
                  its own set that terminates in those trust anchors.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The RP will now construct a self-signed entity statement
                  where the metadata statement chosen is influenced by the OPs
                  metadata and the <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx> included
                  are picked by the
                  process described above.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The entity statement is sent, using POST, to the
                  <spanx style="verb">federation_registration_endpoint</spanx>
                  defined in this document. The content type MUST be set to
                  <spanx style="verb">application/jose</spanx>.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="cliregresp" title="Client Registration Response">
            <section title="The OP Constructing the Response">
              <t>
                <list style="numbers">
                  <t>
                    After the OP receives the request, it collects and
                    evaluates the trust chains starting with the
                    <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx>
                    in the registration request.
                    After it has verified at least one trust chain it
                    MUST verify that the signature on the received registration
                    request is correct.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    If it finds more than one acceptable trust chain, it MUST
                    choose one trust anchor from those chains as the one it will
                    proceed with.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    At this point, if there already exists a client
                    registration under the same entity identifier then that registration
                    MUST be regarded as invalid.
                    <spanx style="verb">Note</spanx>
                    that key material from
                    the
                    previous registration MUST be kept to make key rollover
                    possible.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    The OP will now construct a metadata policy that, if
                    applied to the RP's metadata statement, will result in
                    metadata that the OP finds acceptable.
                    <spanx style="verb">Note</spanx>
                    that the client_id the OP chooses does not have to be
                    the same as the entity identifier of the RP.
                    To the entity statement it will add one or more
                    <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx>, from its
                    collection, that terminate in the
                    trust anchor chosen above.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    It will sign and return the registration response (a signed
                    entity statement) to the RP.
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </section>

            <section title="The RP Parsing the Response">
              <t>
                <list style="numbers">
                  <t>
                    The RP verifies the correctness of the received entity
                    statement, making sure that the trust chains starting at the
                    <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx>
                    terminates in trust anchors that were
                    referenced in the entity statement it sent to the OP.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    The RP MUST NOT apply metadata policies from the trust
                    chains that the OP provides because those are not valid for
                    the RP's metadata.
                    The RP MUST apply policies to the metadata using one of its
                    own trust chains that ends in the trust anchor that the OP
                    chose.
                    Once it has applied those policies it can the apply
                    the policy returned from the OP.
                    When it has applied all the metadata policies to its
                    metadata statement, it then stores
                    the result and can continue communicating with the OP
                    using the agreed-upon metadata.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    At this point the RP also knows which trust chain it should
                    use when evaluating the OP's metadata. It can therefore
                    apply the metadata policies on the OP's metadata using the
                    relevant trust chain and store the result as the OPs
                    metadata.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    If the RP does not accept the received entity statement for some reason,
		    then it has the choice to restart the
                    registration process or to give up.
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="After Client Registration">
          <t>
            A client registration using this specification is not expected to
            be valid forever. The entity statements exchanged all have
            expiration times, which means that the registration will eventually
            time out. An OP can also for administrative reasons decide that a
            client registration is not valid anymore. An example of this could
            be that the OP leaves the federation in use.
          </t>

          <section title="What the RP MUST Do">
            <t>
              At regular intervals, the RP MUST:
            </t>
            <t>
              <list style="numbers">
                <t>
                  Starting with the OP's entity statement, resolve and verify
                  the trust chains it chooses to use when constructing the
                  registration request. If those trust chains do not exist
                  anymore or do not verify, then the registration should be
                  regarded as invalid and a new registration process should be
                  started.
                </t>
                <t>
                  If the OP's entity statement was properly formed the RP must
                  now verify that the entity statement it received about itself
                  from the OP is still valid.
                  Again, if that is not the case the registration
                  should be regarded as invalid and a new registration process
                  should be started.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>
              What is regarded as reasonable intervals will depend on
              federation policies and risk assessment by the maintainer of
              the RP.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="What the OP MUST Do">
            <t>
              At regular intervals, the OP MUST:
            </t>
            <t>
              <list style="numbers">
                <t>
                  If the signature on the registration request has expired it
                  MUST mark the registration as invalid and demand that the
                  RP MUST re-register. Else
                </t>
                <t>
                  starting with the RP's client registration request, the OP
                  MUST
                  verify that there still is a valid trust chain terminating in
                  the trust anchor the OP chose during the registration process.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Expiration Times">
          <t>
            An OP MUST NOT assign an expiration time
            to an RP's registration that is later than the trust
            chain's expiration time.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        TBD Register federation_types_supported for OP metadata with initial
        values automatic, explicit.
      </t>
      <t>
        TBD Register federation_type for RP registration metadata.
      </t>
      <t>
        TBD Register federation_registration_endpoint for the OP metadata.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        TBD
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8615.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7517.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7591.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8414.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Core"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
              Ltd.
            </organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B."
                  surname="de Medeiros">
            <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
            <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="3" month="August" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Discovery"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-discovery-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
              Ltd.
            </organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Edmund Jay" initials="E." surname="Jay">
            <organization abbrev="Illumila">Illumila</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="3" month="August" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenID.Registration"
                 target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-registration-1_0.html">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Connect Dynamic Client Registration 1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
            <organization abbrev="NRI">Nomura Research Institute,
              Ltd.
            </organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
            <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
            <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="3" month="August" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"?>
    </references>

    <section
            title="Provider Information Discovery and Client Registration in a Federation">
      <t>
        Let us assume the following: The project LIGO would like to offer access
        to its wiki to all OPs in EduGAIN. LIGO is registered to the InCommon
        federation.
      </t>

      <figure>
        <preamble>
          The players
        </preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                       EduGAIN
                          |
       +------------------+------------------+
       |                                     |
    SWAMID                               InCommon
       |                                     |
     umu.se                                  |
       |                                     |
   op.umu.se                           wiki.ligo.org
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        Both SWAMID and InCommon are identity federation in their own right.
        They also have that in common that they both are members of
        the EduGAIN federation.
      </t>
      <t>
        SWAMID and InCommon are different in how they register entities.
        SWAMID registers organizations and lets the organizations register
        entities that belong to the organization, while InCommon registers all
        entities directly and not beneath any organization entity.
        Hence the differences in depth in the federations.
      </t>
      <t>
        Let us assume a researcher from Ume&aring; University would like to
        login at
        the LIGO Wiki. At the Wiki, the researcher will use some kind of
        discovery service to find the home identity provider (op.umu.se)
      </t>
      <t>
        Once the RP-part of the Wiki knows which OP it should talk to it has
        to find out a couple of things about the OP. All if those things
        can be found in the metadata. But finding the metadata is not enough;
        the RP also has to trust the metadata.
      </t>
      <t>
        Let us start with discovering Provider information.
      </t>

      <section title="The LIGO Wiki Discovers the OP's Metadata"
               anchor="op_discovery">
        <t>
          Metadata discovery is a sequence of steps that starts with the RP
          fetching the self-signed entity statement of the leaf (in this case
          https://op.umu.se) using the process defined in
          <xref target="federation_configuration"/>.
          What follows thereafter is this sequence of steps:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Pick out the immediate superior entities using the authority
              hints
            </t>
            <t>
              Fetch the configuration for each such entity. This uses the
              process defined in
              <xref target="federation_configuration"/>
            </t>
            <t>
              Using the federation API endpoint of the superiors do
              a fetch request
              <xref target="fetch_statement"/>
              on the endpoint asking for information about the subordinate
              entity.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          How many times this has to be repeated depends on the depth of the
          federation. What follows below is the result of each step the RP
          has to do to find the OP's metadata using the federation set up
          described above.
        </t>
        <t>
          When building the trust chain, the entity statements issued
          by a superior about its subordinate is used together with the
          self-signed entity statement issued by the leaf.
        </t>
        <t>
          The self-signed entity statement concerning intermediates are not
          part of the trust chain.
        </t>
        <section title="Configuration Information for op.umu.se">
          <t>The LIGO WIKI RP fetches the self-signed entity statement from the
            OP (op.umu.se)
            using the process defined in <xref
                    target="federation_configuration"/>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>The result is this entity statement.</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "authority_hints": [
        "https://umu.se"
    ],
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://op.umu.se",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "dEEtRjlzY3djcENuT01wOGxrZlkxb3RIQVJlMTY0...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "x97YKqc9Cs-DNtFrQ7_vhXoH9bwkDWW6En2jJ044yH..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata": {
        "openid_provider": {
            "authorization_endpoint":
              "https://op.umu.se/openid/authorization",
            "federation_types_supported": [
                "automatic",
                "explicit"
            ],
            "grant_types_supported": [
                "authorization_code",
                "implicit",
                "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
            ],
            "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": [
                "ES256"
            ],
            "logo_uri":
              "https://www.umu.se/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
            "policy_uri":
              "https://www.umu.se/en/website/legal-information/",
            "response_types_supported": [
                "code",
                "code id_token",
                "token"
            ],
            "subject_types_supported": [
                "pairwise",
                "public"
            ],
            "token_endpoint": "https://op.umu.se/openid/token",
            "federation_registration_endpoint":
              "https://op.umu.se/openid/fedreg"
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://op.umu.se"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The <spanx style="verb">authority_hints</spanx> points to the
            intermediate https://umu.se. So that is the next step.
          </t>
          <t>
            This entity statement is the first link in the trust chain.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Configuration Information for 'https://umu.se'">
          <t>The LIGO RP fetches the self-signed entity statement from
            "https://umu.se"
            using the process defined in <xref
                    target="federation_configuration"/>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "authority_hints": [
        "https://swamid.se"
    ],
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://umu.se",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "endwNUZrNTJsX2NyQlp4bjhVcTFTTVltR2gxV2RV...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "vXdXzZwQo0hxRSmZEcDIsnpg-CMEkor50SOG-1XUlM..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata": {
        "federation_entity": {
            "contacts": "ops@umu.se",
            "federation_api_endpoint": "https://umu.se/oidc/fedapi",
            "homepage_uri": "https://www.umu.se",
            "name": "UmU"
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://umu.se"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The only piece of information that is used from this entity
            statement is
            the <spanx style="verb">federation_api_endpoint</spanx>,
	    which is used in the next step.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section
                title="Entity Statement Published by 'https://umu.se' about 'https://op.umu.se'">
          <t>
            The RP uses the federation API and the "fetch" command as defined in
            <xref target="fetch_statement"/>
            to fetch information about
            "https://op.umu.se" from the API endpoint published in
            https://umu.se's configuration.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "authority_hints": [
        "https://swamid.se"
    ],
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://umu.se",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "dEEtRjlzY3djcENuT01wOGxrZlkxb3RIQVJlMTY0...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "x97YKqc9Cs-DNtFrQ7_vhXoH9bwkDWW6En2jJ044yH..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata_policy": {
        "openid_provider": {
            "contacts": {
                "add": [
                    "ops@swamid.se"
                ]
            },
            "organization": {
                "value": "University of Ume\u00e5"
            },
            "subject_types_supported": {
                "value": [
                    "pairwise"
                ]
            },
            "token_endpoint_auth_methods_supported": {
                "default": [
                    "private_key_jwt"
                ],
                "subset_of": [
                    "private_key_jwt",
                    "client_secret_jwt"
                ],
                "superset_of": [
                    "private_key_jwt"
                ]
            }
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://op.umu.se"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            This is the second link in the trust chain.
          </t>
          <t>
            Notable here is that this path leads to two trust anchors using the
            same
            next step ("https://swamid.se").
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Configuration Information for 'https://swamid.se'">
          <t>The LIGO Wiki RP fetches the self-signed entity statement from
            "https://swamid.se"
            using the process defined in <xref
                    target="federation_configuration"/>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "authority_hints": [
        "https://edugain.geant.org"
    ],
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://swamid.se",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "N1pQTzFxUXZ1RXVsUkVuMG5uMnVDSURGRVdhUzdO...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "3EQc6cR_GSBq9km9-WCHY_lWJZWkcn0M05TGtH6D9S..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata": {
        "federation_entity": {
            "contacts": "ops@swamid.se",
            "federation_api_endpoint":
              "https://swamid.sunet.se/fedapi",
            "homepage_uri": "https://www.sunet.se/swamid/",
            "name": "SWAMID"
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://swamid.se"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The only piece of information that is used from this entity
            statement is
            the <spanx style="verb">federation_api_endpoint</spanx>,
	    which is used in the next step.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section
                title="Entity Statement Published by 'https://swamid.se' about 'https://umu.se'">
          <t>
            The LIGO Wiki RP uses the federation API and the "fetch" command as
            defined in
            <xref target="fetch_statement"/>
            to fetch information about
            "https://umu.se" from the API endpoint published in
            https://swamid.se's configuration.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "authority_hints": [
        "https://edugain.geant.org"
    ],
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://swamid.se",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "endwNUZrNTJsX2NyQlp4bjhVcTFTTVltR2gxV2RV...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "vXdXzZwQo0hxRSmZEcDIsnpg-CMEkor50SOG-1XUlM..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata_policy": {
        "openid_provider": {
            "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": {
                "subset_of": [
                    "RS256",
                    "ES256",
                    "ES384",
                    "ES512"
                ]
            },
            "token_endpoint_auth_methods_supported": {
                "subset_of": [
                    "client_secret_jwt",
                    "private_key_jwt"
                ]
            },
            "userinfo_signing_alg_values_supported": {
                "subset_of": [
                    "ES256",
                    "ES384",
                    "ES512"
                ]
            }
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://umu.se"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            This is the third link in the trust chain.
          </t>
          <t>
            If we assume that the issuer of this entity statement is not in the
            list of trust anchors the LIGO Wiki RP has access to we have to go
            one step further.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section
                title="Configuration Information for 'https://edugain.geant.org'">
          <t>RP fetches the self-signed entity statement from
            "https://edugain.geant.org"
            using the process defined in <xref
                    target="federation_configuration"/>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://edugain.geant.org",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "Sl9DcjFxR3hrRGdabUNIR21KT3dvdWMyc2VUM2Fr...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "xKlwocDXUw-mrvDSO4oRrTRrVuTwotoBFpozvlq-1q..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata": {
        "federation_entity": {
            "federation_api_endpoint":
              "https://geant.org/edugain/api"
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://edugain.geant.org"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Again, the only thing we need is the
            <spanx style="verb">federation_api_endpoint</spanx>.
            As described in
            <xref target="key_rollover_anchor"/>,
            note should also be
            taken to <spanx style="verb">jwks</spanx> as the trust anchor may be
            performing a key rollover.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section
                title="Entity Statement Published by 'https://edugain.geant.org' about 'https://swamid.se'">
          <t>
            The LIGO Wiki RP uses the federation API and the "fetch" command as
            defined in
            <xref target="fetch_statement"/>
            to fetch information about
            "https://swamid.se" from the API endpoint published in
            https://edugain.geant.org's configuration.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "exp": 1568397247,
    "iat": 1568310847,
    "iss": "https://edugain.geant.org",
    "jwks": {
        "keys": [
            {
                "e": "AQAB",
                "kid": "N1pQTzFxUXZ1RXVsUkVuMG5uMnVDSURGRVdhUzdO...",
                "kty": "RSA",
                "n": "3EQc6cR_GSBq9km9-WCHY_lWJZWkcn0M05TGtH6D9S..."
            }
        ]
    },
    "metadata_policy": {
        "openid_provider": {
            "contacts": {
                "add": "ops@edugain.geant.org"
            }
        },
        "openid_relying_part": {
            "contacts": {
                "add": "ops@edugain.geant.org"
            }
        }
    },
    "sub": "https://swamid.se"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            If we assume that the issuer of this statement appears in the list
            of trust anchors the LIGO Wiki RP has access to this would be
            the fourth and final entity statement in the trust chain.
          </t>
          <t>
            We now have the whole chain from the self-signed entity statement of
            the
            leaf up until the last one which is issued by a trust anchor. All in
            all,
            we have:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Self-signed entity statement by the leaf (https://op.umu.se)
              </t>
              <t>Statement issued by https://umu.se about https://op.umu.se</t>
              <t>Statement issued by https://swamid.se about https://umu.se</t>
              <t>Statement issued by https://edugain.geant.org about
                https://swamid.se
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Using the public keys of the trust anchor that the LIGO Wiki RP has
            been
            provided with in some secure out-of-band way, it can now verify the
            trust chain as described in
            <xref target="trust_chain_validation"/>.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Verified Metadata for op.umu.se">
          <t>Having verified the chain, the LIGO Wiki RP can proceed with the
            next step.
          </t>
          <t>Merging the metadata policies from the tree entity statements we
            have, by
            a superior about its subordinate, and applying the combined policy
            to the
            metadata statement that the leaf entity presented, we get:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "authorization_endpoint":
      "https://op.umu.se/openid/authorization",
    "contacts": "ops@edugain.geant.org",
    "federation_types_supported": [
        "automatic",
        "explicit"
    ],
    "grant_types_supported": [
        "authorization_code",
        "implicit",
        "urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer"
    ],
    "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": [
        "ES256"
    ],
    "logo_uri":
      "https://www.umu.se/img/umu-logo-left-neg-SE.svg",
    "policy_uri":
      "https://www.umu.se/en/website/legal-information/",
    "response_types_supported": [
        "code",
        "code id_token",
        "token"
    ],
    "subject_types_supported": [
        "pairwise",
        "public"
    ],
    "token_endpoint": "https://op.umu.se/openid/token",
    "federation_registration_endpoint":
        "https://op.umu.se/openid/fedreg"
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            We have now reached the end of the Provider Discovery process.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="The Two Ways of Doing Client Registration">
        <t>
          As described in
          <xref target="client_registration"/>,
          there are two
          ways which can be used to do client registration:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Automatic">
              <vspace/>
              No negotiation between the RP and the OP is made regarding
              what features the client should use in future communication are
              done. The RP's published metadata filtered by the chosen trust
              chain's
              metadata policies defines the metadata that is to be used.
            </t>
            <t hangText="Explicit">
              <vspace/>
              The RP will access the
              <spanx style="verb">federation_registration_endpoint</spanx>,
              which provides the metadata for the RP to use. The OP MAY return a
              metadata policy that adds restrictions over and above what the
              trust chain already has defined.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <section
                title="RP Sends Authentication Request (Automatic Registration)">
          <t>
            The LIGO Wiki RP does not do any registration but goes directly to
            sending an authentication request.
          </t>
          <t>
            Here is an example of an authentication request:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /authorize?
  response_type=code
  &scope=openid%20profile%20email
  &client_id=https%3A%2F%2Fwiki.ligo.org%2F
  &state=2ff7e589-3848-46da-a3d2-949e1235e671
  &redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fwiki.ligo.org%2Fopenid%2Fcallback
  &client_assertion=eyJhbGciOiJSUzI1NiIs ... qx7xHcvPOdIhnpg
  &client_assertion_type=
    urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth%3Aclient-assertion-type%3Ajwt-bearer
  HTTP/1.1
Host: op.umu.se
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The OP receiving this authentication request will, unless the
            RP is cached or statically configured, start to dynamically fetch
            and
            establish trust with the RP.
          </t>
        <section title="OP Fetches Entity Statements">
          <t>
            The OP needs to establish a trust chain for the RP (wiki.ligo.org).
            The OP in this example are configured with public key of 2
            federations:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>https://edugain.geant.org</t>
              <t>https://swamid.se</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            The OP starts to resolve metadata for the client identifier
            https://wiki.ligo.org by fetching the self-issued entity statement
            using
            the process described in <xref target="federation_configuration"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The process is the same as described in
            <xref target="op_discovery"/>
            and will result in a trust chain with the following entity
            statements:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Self-signed entity statement by the leaf
                https://wiki.ligo.org
              </t>
              <t>Statement issued by https://incommon.org about
                https://wiki.ligo.org
              </t>
              <t>Statement issued by https://edugain.geant.org about
                https://incommon.org
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="OP Evaluates the RP Metadata" anchor="rp_metadata_eval">
          <t>
            Using the public keys of the trust anchor that the LIGO Wiki RP has
            been
            provided with in some secure out-of-band way, it can now verify the
            trust chain as described in
            <xref target="trust_chain_validation"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            We will not list the complete entity statements but only the
	    <spanx style="verb">metadata</spanx>
            and <spanx style="verb">metadata_policy</spanx> parts.
	    There are two metadata policies:
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="edugain.geant.org">
                <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
    "metadata_policy": {
        "openid_provider": {
            "contacts": {
                "add": "ops@edugain.geant.org"
            }
        },
        "openid_relying_party": {
            "contacts": {
                "add": "ops@edugain.geant.org"
            }
        }
    }
                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
              </t>
              <t hangText="incommon.org">
                <figure>
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
    "metadata_policy": {
        "openid_relying_party": {
            "application_type": {
                "one_of": [
                    "web",
                    "native"
                ]
            },
            "contacts": {
                "add": "ops@incommon.org"
            },
            "grant_types": {
                "subset_of": [
                    "authorization_code",
                    "refresh_token"
                ]
            }
        }
    }
                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            If you combine these and apply them to the metadata for
            wiki.ligo.org :
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"metadata": {
    "openid_relying_party": {
        "application_type": "web",
        "client_name": "LIGO Wiki",
        "contacts": [
            "ops@ligo.org"
        ],
        "grant_types": [
            "authorization_code",
            "refresh_token"
        ],
        "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": [
            "RS256",
            "RS512"
        ],
        "jwks_uri": "https://wiki.ligo.org/jwks.json",
        "redirect_uris": [
            "https://wiki.ligo.org/callback"
        ],
        "response_types": [
            "code"
        ],
        "subject_type": "public"
    }
}
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            You will get
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "application_type": "web",
    "client_name": "LIGO Wiki",
    "contacts": [
        "ops@ligo.org",
        "ops@incommon.org",
        "ops@edugain.geant.org"
    ],
    "grant_types": [
        "authorization_code",
        "refresh_token"
    ],
    "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": [
        "RS256",
        "RS512"
    ],
    "jwks_uri": "https://wiki.ligo.org/jwks.json",
    "redirect_uris": [
        "https://wiki.ligo.org/callback"
    ],
    "response_types": [
        "code"
    ],
    "subject_type": "public"
}]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Having that, the "registration" is done, and the OP must now use
            the keys found at the URL specified in
            <spanx style="verb">jwks_uri</spanx>
            to verify the client
            assertion in the authentication request.
          </t>
        </section>
        </section>
        <section
                title="Client Starts with Registration (Explicit Client Registration)">
          <t>
            Here the LIGO Wiki RP sends a client registration request to the
            federation_registration_endpoint of the OP (op.umu.se).
            What it sends is a self-signed entity statement.
          </t>
          <t>
            Once the OP has the entity statement, it proceeds with the same
            sequence of steps as laid out in <xref target="op_discovery"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The OP will end up with the same RP metadata as was described in
            <xref target="rp_metadata_eval"/>, but what it now can do is
            return a metadata policy that it wants to be applied to the RP's
            metadata. This metadata policy will be combined with the
            trust chain's combined metadata policy before being applied to the
            RP's metadata.
          </t>
          <t>
            If we assume that the OP has a bit more strict view on which type
            of crypto keys to use, it may want to add a metadata policy that says:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"metadata_policy":
   {
      "openid_relying_party": {
         "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": [
            "RS512"
        ]
      }
}]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            In which case the metadata used by the RP should be described like
            this:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "application_type": "web",
    "client_name": "LIGO Wiki",
    "contacts": [
        "ops@ligo.org",
        "ops@incommon.org",
        "ops@edugain.geant.org"
    ],
    "grant_types": [
        "authorization_code",
        "refresh_token"
    ],
    "id_token_signing_alg_values_supported": [
        "RS512"
    ],
    "jwks_uri": "https://wiki.ligo.org/jwks.json",
    "redirect_uris": [
        "https://wiki.ligo.org/callback"
    ],
    "response_types": [
        "code"
    ],
    "subject_type": "public"
}]]></artwork>
          </figure>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Notices" title="Notices">
      <t>
        Copyright (c) 2019 The OpenID Foundation.
      </t>
      <t>
        The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer,
        implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free,
        worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works from,
        distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or Final
        Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing specifications,
        and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and Final Specifications based
        on such documents, provided that attribution be made to the OIDF as the
        source of the material, but that such attribution does not indicate an
        endorsement by the OIDF.
      </t>
      <t>
        The technology described in this specification was made available
        from contributions from various sources, including members of the OpenID
        Foundation and others. Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps to
        help ensure that the technology is available for distribution, it takes
        no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual property
        or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation
        or use of the technology described in this specification or the extent
        to which any license under such rights might or might not be available;
        neither does it represent that it has made any independent effort to
        identify any such rights. The OpenID Foundation and the contributors to
        this specification make no (and hereby expressly disclaim any)
        warranties (express, implied, or otherwise), including implied
        warranties of merchantability, non-infringement, fitness for a
        particular purpose, or title, related to this specification, and the
        entire risk as to implementing this specification is assumed by the
        implementer. The OpenID Intellectual Property Rights policy requires
        contributors to offer a patent promise not to assert certain patent
        claims against other contributors and against implementers. The OpenID
        Foundation invites any interested party to bring to its attention any
        copyrights, patents, patent applications, or other proprietary rights
        that may cover technology that may be required to practice this
        specification.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        The authors wish to acknowledge the contributions of the following
        individuals and organizations to this specification:
        Heather Flanagan,
        Marcos Sanz,
        Misha Salle,
        Jouke Roorda,
        Peter Schober,
        Michael Schwartz,
        and
        the JRA3T3 task force of GEANT4-2.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TBD" title="Open Issues">
      <t>
        The following open issues remain to be addressed in this specification.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The representation for RPs that are native applications needs to be
            defined.
          </t>
          <t>
            How are federation operator keys retrieved?
          </t>
          <t>
            A mechanism is needed for key rotation of federation operator keys
            for long-term security and maintainability of federations.
          </t>
          <t>
            A mechanism may be needed for bounding key lifetimes.
          </t>
          <t>
            Discuss that key IDs may be chosen as the JWK Thumbprint [RFC 7638]
            of the key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Discuss localization of human-readable strings.
          </t>
          <t>
            SAML2 as used in Research and Education federations uses
            post-/prefix
            matching on metadata in some cases. We might need something
            similar or just use regular expressions.
          </t>
          <t>
            Define the relationship between trust anchors and Federation
            Operators,
            as people will expect to find the Federation Operator term in the
            specification.
          </t>
          <t>
            Add a diagram showing the relationships between FOs, orgs, sub-orgs,
            and leaf entities.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="History" title="Document History">
      <t>[[ To be removed from the final specification ]]</t>
      <t>
        -10
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Incorporated additional review feedback from Marcos Sanz.
	    The primary change was moving constraints to their own section of the entity statement.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        -09
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Incorporated review feedback from Marcos Sanz.
            Major changes were as follows.
          </t>
          <t>
            Separated entity configuration discovery from operations provided
            by the federation API.
          </t>
          <t>
            Defined new authentication error codes.
          </t>
          <t>
            Also incorporated review feedback from Michael B. Jones.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        -08
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Incorporated review feedback from Michael B. Jones.
            Major changes were as follows.
          </t>
          <t>
            Deleted <spanx style="verb">sub_is_leaf</spanx> entity statement
            since it was redundant.
          </t>
          <t>
            Added <spanx style="verb">federation_type</spanx> RP registration
            metadata value
            and <spanx style="verb">federation_types_supported</spanx> OP
            metadata value.
          </t>
          <t>
            Deleted <spanx style="verb">openid_discovery</spanx> metadata type
            identifier
            since its purpose is already served by
            <spanx style="verb">openid_provider</spanx>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Entity identifier paths are now included when using the Federation
            API,
            enabling use in multi-tenant deployments sharing a common domain
            name.
          </t>
          <t>
            Renamed <spanx style="verb">sub_is_leaf</spanx> to
            <spanx style="verb">is_leaf</spanx>
            in the Entity Listings Request operation parameters.
          </t>
          <t>
            Added <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> and
            <spanx style="verb">policy_language_crit</spanx>,
            enabling control over which entity statement and policy language
            extensions
            MUST be understood and processed.
          </t>
          <t>
            Renamed <spanx style="verb">openid_client</spanx> to
            <spanx style="verb">openid_relying_party</spanx>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Renamed <spanx style="verb">oauth_service</spanx> to
            <spanx style="verb">oauth_authorization_server</spanx>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Renamed <spanx style="verb">implicit</spanx> registration to
            <spanx style="verb">automatic</spanx>
            registration
            to avoid naming confusion with the implicit grant type.
          </t>
          <t>
            Renamed <spanx style="verb">op</spanx> to
            <spanx style="verb">operation</spanx>
            to avoid naming confusion with the use of "OP" as an acronym for
            "OpenID Provider".
          </t>
          <t>
            Renamed <spanx style="verb">url</spanx> to
            <spanx style="verb">uri</spanx>
            in several identifiers.
          </t>
          <t>
            Restored Open Issues appendix.
          </t>
          <t>
            Corrected document formatting issues.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        -07
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Split metadata into metadata and metadata_policy
          </t>
          <t>
            Updated example
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        -06
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Some rewrites
          </t>
          <t>
            Added example of explicit client registration
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        -05
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            A major rewrite.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        -04
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Changed client metadata names
            <spanx style="verb">scopes</spanx>
            to <spanx style="verb">rp_scopes</spanx> and
            <spanx style="verb">claims</spanx>
            to <spanx style="verb">rp_claims</spanx>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Added Open Issues appendix.
          </t>
          <t>
            Added additional references.
          </t>
          <t>
            Editorial improvements.
          </t>
          <t>
            Added standard Notices section, which is present in all OpenID
            specifications.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
